<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<indiaspend>
  <article>
    <title>Can Modi’s Nuclear Deal Clean Up India’s Air?</title>
    <authorname>Amit Bhandari</authorname>
    <date>May 8, 2015</date>
    <category>Infrastructure</category>
    <image>&lt;img href='2015-05-08-img1.jpg' /&gt;</image>
    <width>624</width>
    <height>377</height>
    <content>
      <value>&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;An agreement with the Canadian company CAMECO, one of the world&amp;#8217;s largest uranium producers, was one of the highlights of Prime Minister Narendra Modi&amp;#8217;s recent three-nation (Germany, France, and Canada) &lt;a href="http://www.indiaspend.com/special-reports/pm-modis-last-stop-canada-to-boost-make-in-india-58914"&gt;trip&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;div style="width:625px;margin-top:15px"&gt;&lt;div id="InRead"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;CAMECO will supply India with 3,000 tonnes of uranium over six years, &lt;a href="http://164.100.47.132/LssNew/psearch/QResult16.aspx?qref=14536"&gt;enough&lt;/a&gt; to keep 1,700 megawatts (MW) of India&amp;#8217;s 5,780 MW of nuclear-power plants running.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;A similar agreement was concluded with Uzbekistan in 2013, and India is trying to close a fuel supply agreement with Australia, which has the world&amp;#8217;s largest reserves of uranium. These agreements are in addition to those already inked with Russia and Kazakhstan.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;</value>
    </content>
    <image>&lt;img href='2015-05-08-img2.jpg' /&gt;</image>
    <width>527</width>
    <height>323</height>
    <content>
      <value>&lt;p&gt;These agreements may be part of the solution to India&amp;#8217;s air pollution &lt;a href="http://www.indiaspend.com/cover-story/a-bangalore-neighbourhoods-toxic-air-portends-indias-future-55198"&gt;problems&lt;/a&gt;. India is trying to move away from using coal, which accounts for almost 80% of India&amp;#8217;s &lt;a href="http://www.cea.nic.in/reports/monthly/generation_rep/tentative/mar15/opm_01.pdf"&gt;electricity generation&lt;/a&gt; and is highly polluting.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;Nuclear power accounts for 3.5% of India&amp;#8217;s electricity generation and 1.3% of India&amp;#8217;s total energy consumption, but the government has set some ambitious targets.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;It wants to &lt;a href="http://pib.nic.in/newsite/PrintRelease.aspx?relid=118504"&gt;triple&lt;/a&gt; nuclear power plant capacity by 2024 from 4,780 MW in 2014 (5,780 MW now). A more recent and extremely ambitious goal is a target of 63,000 MW by 2031-32.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;Nuclear energy does not emit carbon dioxide and other pollutants&amp;#8212;major concerns, given the &lt;a href="http://www.indiaspend.com/cover-story/a-bangalore-neighbourhoods-toxic-air-portends-indias-future-55198"&gt;air-quality crisis&lt;/a&gt; in Indian cities and the widespread economic effects of local and global &lt;a href="http://www.indiaspend.com/cover-story/for-indias-farmers-harder-life-ahead-latest-studies-77368"&gt;climate change&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;However, nuclear power comes with potentially catastrophic &lt;a href="http://www.physics.isu.edu/radinf/np-risk.htm"&gt;safety risks&lt;/a&gt;, which India hopes to keep under check. Other countries weigh the risks similarly, although Germany intends to &lt;a href="http://www.bbc.com/news/world-europe-13592208"&gt;close nuclear plants&lt;/a&gt; by 2022.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;</value>
    </content>
    <image>&lt;img href='2015-05-08-img3.jpg' /&gt;</image>
    <width>519</width>
    <height>338</height>
    <content>
      <value>&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;China, the biggest user of coal globally (and the biggest polluter) is also trying to aggressively &lt;a href="http://www.ecns.cn/business/2015/04-23/162842.shtml"&gt;move&lt;/a&gt; to nuclear power. China&amp;#8217;s target: 58,000 MW of nuclear power by 2020 and 150,000 MW by 2030&amp;#8211;this is a key component of China&amp;#8217;s plans to &lt;a href="http://news.xinhuanet.com/english/china/2014-11/19/c_133801014.htm"&gt;increase&lt;/a&gt; the share of non-fossil fuels (excluding coal, oil, gas) from less than 10% now to 15% by 2020 and 20% by 2030.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The problem with nuclear fuel&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;Arranging affordable nuclear-fuel supply has been a &lt;a href="http://www.indiaspend.com/cover-story/how-japanese-energy-demand-has-shut-down-indias-gas-plants-69008"&gt;challenge&lt;/a&gt; for India.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;India is currently saddled with 23,000 MW gas-based power plants, &lt;a href="http://www.cea.nic.in/reports/monthly/generation_rep/tentative/mar15/opm_17.pdf"&gt;almost&lt;/a&gt; idle for want of fuel.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;Electricity from gas is also 2-3 times &lt;a href="http://www.thehindubusinessline.com/industry-and-economy/govt-works-out-4-options-to-revive-dabhol-power-plant/article5549984.ece"&gt;costlier&lt;/a&gt; than nuclear power depending on gas prices, a concern in an emerging economy.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;But scaling up nuclear energy is a problem. Of 5,780 MW of nuclear-power capacity that India operates, 3,380 MW relies on &lt;a href="http://164.100.47.132/LssNew/psearch/QResult16.aspx?qref=12373"&gt;imported&lt;/a&gt; fuel. Domestic uranium supplies are enough only for the remaining 2,400 MW.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;Historically, India&amp;#8217;s nuclear power programme has been constrained by a uranium shortage. The programme started to grow only after the Indo-US nuclear agreement of 2008, which allowed India to import nuclear fuel and ink agreements with fuel suppliers (see &lt;strong&gt;Table 1&lt;/strong&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;India has 3,800 MW of nuclear-power capacity under construction and another 43,100 MW is proposed. Of this, 1,000 MW of under-construction capacity and 31,900 MW of proposed nuclear capacity will be built in collaboration with companies from the US, France and Russia. For these reactors, the contractors must provide fuel throughout a plant&amp;#8217;s life, which can last up to 50 years.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;For the remaining 14,000 MW of indigenously designed nuclear capacity, India needs to source fuel. Domestic uranium supplies, as we explained, are inadequate.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;Moreover, domestic uranium also has other uses&amp;#8212;to build nuclear weapons&amp;#8212;and using it only for fuel is not something India would like to do.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;(&lt;strong&gt;Bhandari&lt;/strong&gt; is a media, research and finance professional. He holds a B-Tech from IIT-BHU and an MBA from IIM-Ahmedabad.)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Image Credit: &lt;a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/iaea_imagebank/8386517520/"&gt;IAEA/Petr Pavlicek&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;hr color="#555555" align="left" width="620px" /&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;#8220;Liked this story? Indiaspend.com is a non-profit, and we depend on readers like you to drive our public-interest journalism efforts. &lt;a href="http://www.indiaspend.com/donate1" target="_blank"&gt;Donate&lt;/a&gt; Rs 500; Rs 1,000, Rs 2,000.&amp;#8221;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
</value>
    </content>
  </article>
</indiaspend>
