<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<indiaspend>
  <article>
    <title>95% Of Government’s Attention Should Be Focused On Fixing Domestic Issues, Says Ahluwalia</title>
    <authorname/>
    <date>March 24, 2014</date>
    <category>Politics</category>
    <content>
      <value>&lt;p&gt;Montek Singh Ahluwalia, Deputy Chairman, Planning Commission, in conversation with Govindraj Ethiraj at The Growth Net.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Govind&lt;/b&gt;: So, we are entering a new phase. It&amp;#8217;s not an unusual phase but it&amp;#8217;s a new phase, the Government might change. What is the situation, as you see it today? Is there a tailwind or some headwind? Where are things headed, and where are they likely to land?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Montek&lt;/b&gt;: Globally you mean?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Govind&lt;/b&gt;: India&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Montek&lt;/b&gt;: &amp;nbsp;India is a large and complex country. So, there are always tailwinds that help you and headwinds that hold you back. I think the new Government has to address these issues. I think you should stop getting too worried about hundreds of constraints. You know, we are still a poor country. So, there are hundreds of concerns. I think what we need to look at is what are the three or four critical things which are holding back growth &amp;nbsp;at 5%, which is the sort of average of the last two years, &amp;nbsp;to I think between 7% and 8%, &amp;nbsp;which I think India is perfectly capable of achieving. And that does not require hundreds of things. In fact, many of those hundreds of things are really minor things that require progress on 7 or 8 really big things. Once you start building on the longer term ones, these things get done very quickly.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Govind&lt;/b&gt;: So, how many of those things are underway?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Montek&lt;/b&gt;: Well, you know, because we have such an extensive debating tradition in the country, everything is underway.&amp;nbsp; Nothing that I have said isn&amp;#8217;t found somewhere in the plan but you know I would say that we probably have to get the macro into better shape. The good news is that it is getting better but it is certainly not in a situation that one would say is comfortable.&amp;nbsp; So, that has to have priority. Once the macro gets out of shape, many other things just won&amp;#8217;t happen.&amp;nbsp; That is point number one.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Point number two is that we need to revive the thrust on infrastructure development; &amp;nbsp;good infrastructure brings in private investment from anywhere in the country. Whichever state that offers good infrastructure, all Indian investors from every other state will want to go there.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Govind&lt;/b&gt;: Is that a reference to states like Gujarat?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Montek&lt;/b&gt;:&amp;nbsp; We recently did a study of several states in order to get a sense of ease of doing business. We divided the states into the top third, the middle third and the last third. Now, certainly Gujarat is one among the top third. So, are Maharashtra, Karnataka and Andhra Pradesh. &amp;nbsp;There are a lot of states that are doing well, some states are middling and there are some that are not doing well at all.&lt;/p&gt;</value>
    </content>
  </article>
</indiaspend>
