<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<indiaspend>
  <article>
    <title> In 3 Months, Swine Flu Deaths Top Worst Annual Toll</title>
    <authorname>Chaitanya Mallapur</authorname>
    <date>March 26, 2015</date>
    <category>Politics</category>
    <image>&lt;img href='AnnualTollcoverimage.jpg' /&gt;</image>
    <width>620</width>
    <height>376</height>
    <content>
      <value>&lt;p&gt;The H1N1 influenza, commonly known as swine flu, has claimed 1,947 lives and infected 32,663 people across India according to official data (as on March 23, 2015).&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;div style="width:625px;margin-top:15px"&gt;&lt;div id="InRead"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;In less than three months this year, the toll has crossed the 2010 peak of 1,763 deaths.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
</value>
    </content>
    <image>&lt;img href='AnnualTollgraph1.jpg' /&gt;</image>
    <width>508</width>
    <height>289</height>
    <content>
      <value>&lt;p&gt;H1N1&amp;#8212;a virus with a mix of swine, bird and human genes&amp;#8212;is a seasonal influenza that that is threatening to become pandemic in India. Medical professionals &lt;a href="http://www.telegraphindia.com/1150302/jsp/calcutta/story_6397.jsp#.VRKEn_mUeSo"&gt;predicted&lt;/a&gt; it would die down with the start of warm weather; instead the toll has spiralled.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;Varieties of influenza cause between 250,000 and 500,000 deaths every year and an annual global attack rate of 5-10% in adults and 20-30% in children, according to the &lt;a href="http://www.who.int/ith/diseases/si_iAh1n1/en/"&gt;World Health Organisation&lt;/a&gt; (WHO). The toll skyrockets in pandemic years.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;H1N1 is a &lt;a href="http://www.who.int/ith/diseases/si_iAh1n1/en/"&gt;respiratory infection&lt;/a&gt; that spreads through coughs, sneezes and touch. Short-distance airborne transmission of the influenza virus may occur, particularly in crowded enclosed spaces.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;The western state of Gujarat is the worst-affected, reporting 415 deaths and 6,417 cases of swine flu this year. H1N1 fears have now put &lt;a href="http://indianexpress.com/article/cities/ahmedabad/12-more-die-of-swine-flu-public-events-put-on-hold-2/"&gt;public events&lt;/a&gt; on hold in Gujarat. This &lt;a href="http://america.aljazeera.com/articles/2015/3/23/deadly-outbreak-of-swine-flu-in-india-may-be-due-to-a-mutated-strain.html"&gt;report&lt;/a&gt; says the toll could even be higher than officially reported.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
</value>
    </content>
    <image>&lt;img href='AnnualTollgraph2.jpg' /&gt;</image>
    <width>638</width>
    <height>287</height>
    <content>
      <value>&lt;p&gt;Rajasthan is second after Gujarat with 403 deaths, followed by Maharashtra (360) and Madhya Pradesh (286).&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;IndiaSpend&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="http://www.indiaspend.com/cover-story/indian-swine-flu-virus-reveals-dangerous-new-mutation-78121"&gt;recently reported&lt;/a&gt; a mutation in the H1N1 virus, which could be one explanation for its growing virulence.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;The genetic sequences&amp;#8212;or alphabet chains&amp;#8212;of the Indian H1N1 strain revealed important changes linked to greater virulence, according to an &lt;a href="http://www.cell.com/cell-host-microbe/abstract/S1931-3128%2815%2900076-1"&gt;MIT paper&lt;/a&gt; released in the international journal &lt;em&gt;Cell Host and Microbe&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;The Indian government rejected that study, questioning the authenticity of the sample&amp;#8212;supplied by an Indian government laboratory&amp;#8212;and called it an &amp;#8220;incorrect conclusion&amp;#8221;, but did not answer many &lt;a href="http://www.livemint.com/Opinion/PyAP0DIxzhLrcxflv5xtgL/The-curious-case-of-the-H1N1-mutation.html"&gt;questions&lt;/a&gt; and held back genetic data.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;As on March 23, 2015, 6,088 people have died and 92,340 have been affected by H1N1 influenza in India since May 2009.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
</value>
    </content>
    <image>&lt;img href='AnnualTollgraph3.jpg' /&gt;</image>
    <width>640</width>
    <height>278</height>
    <content>
      <value>&lt;p&gt;In 2015, Rajasthan reported the most swine flu cases (6,461) followed by Gujarat (6,417).&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;Prior to 2015, for the period from May 2009 to December 2014, Maharashtra had reported the most deaths from swine flu&amp;#8212;1,271. Gujarat was next with 773 deaths, followed by Rajasthan (573) and Karnataka (366).&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;Maharashtra was also the worst affected state in terms of swine flu cases for the period from May 2009 to December 2014&amp;#8212;13,743 people were infected. Delhi was next with 12,816 cases followed by Rajasthan (6,050).&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;____________________________________________________________________&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;#8220;Liked this story? Indiaspend.org is a non-profit, and we depend on readers like you to drive our public-interest journalism efforts. &lt;a href="http://www.indiaspend.com/donate1" target="_blank"&gt;Donate&lt;/a&gt; Rs 500; Rs 1,000, Rs 2,000.&amp;#8221;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
</value>
    </content>
  </article>
</indiaspend>
