<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<indiaspend>
  <article>
    <title> 75 Million Bank Accounts For India’s Poor—And Counting</title>
    <authorname>Chaitanya Mallapur</authorname>
    <date>November 17, 2014</date>
    <category>Politics</category>
    <image>&lt;img href='bankaccountscoverimage.jpg' /&gt;</image>
    <width>2200</width>
    <height>1194</height>
    <content>
      <value>&lt;p&gt;The Pradhan Mantri Jan DhanYojana (PMJDY) was launched by Prime Minister NarendraModi on 28th August, 2014 with the &lt;a href=\"http://www.pmjdy.gov.in/pmjdy_mission.aspx\"&gt;objective&lt;/a&gt; of providing India&amp;#8217;s poor with financial services. PMJDY will provide savings bank accounts, loans, insurance and pensions. &lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;In addition, beneficiaries will get RuPay debit card with an in-built accident insurance cover of &amp;#2352; 1 lakh and &amp;#2352; 5,000 over draft facility for Aadhaar-linked accounts. Modi, in his speech today at Allphones Arena in Sydney, Australia, &lt;a href=\"http://pib.nic.in/newsite/mbErel.aspx?relid=111477\"&gt;referred&lt;/a&gt; to his government&amp;#8217;s commitment towards PMJDY.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;Let us now look at the recent targets achieved under PMJDY.&lt;/p&gt;</value>
    </content>
    <image>&lt;img href='bankaccountsgraph1.jpg' /&gt;</image>
    <width>644</width>
    <height>432</height>
    <image>&lt;img href='bankaccountsgraph2.jpg' /&gt;</image>
    <width>634</width>
    <height>427</height>
    <content>
      <value>&lt;p&gt;So far, nearly 75 million accounts (56 million accounts have no money in them) have been opened with Rs 5832 crore in these accounts. As &lt;a href=\"http://www.indiaspend.com/cover-story/jan-dhan-narendra-modis-speed-problem-55585\"&gt;reported&lt;/a&gt; by &lt;strong&gt;IndiaSpend&lt;/strong&gt; earlier,the United Progressive Alliance (UPA) government opened 50.6 million &lt;a href=\"http://www.rbi.org.in/scripts/NotificationUser.aspx?Id=2615&amp;amp;Mode=0\"&gt;no-frills accounts&lt;/a&gt; between 2005 and 2010. More than 42 million Rupay debit cards have been issued.&lt;/p&gt;</value>
    </content>
    <image>&lt;img href='bankaccountsgraph3.jpg' /&gt;</image>
    <width>622</width>
    <height>431</height>
    <content>
      <value>&lt;p&gt;The Ministry of Finance announced that Kerala and Goa have become the first states to &lt;a href=\"http://articles.economictimes.indiatimes.com/2014-11-15/news/56115204_1_pmjdy-mantri-jan-dhan-yojana-finance-ministry\"&gt;provide&lt;/a&gt; one basic bank account to every household, achieving the primary goal of PMJDY within two-and-a-half months of launch. Similarly, the union territories of Chandigarh, Puducherry and Lakshadweep and three districts of Gujarat&amp;#8212;Porbandar, Mehasana and Gandhi Nagar&amp;#8212;have also covered all households under PMJDY with at least one bank account.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;br&gt;&#13;
Image Credit: PIB&lt;br&gt;&#13;
&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;(The graphic has been corrected)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br&gt;</value>
    </content>
  </article>
</indiaspend>
