<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<indiaspend>
  <article>
    <title>Big Fights in Delhi–But Similar Promises</title>
    <authorname>Prachi Salve </authorname>
    <date>February 3, 2015</date>
    <category>Politics</category>
    <image>&lt;img href='BigFightscoverimage.jpg' /&gt;</image>
    <width>620</width>
    <height>330</height>
    <content>
      <value>&lt;p&gt;For all the sound and fury exchanged by the three principal parties in the electoral battle to control Delhi, the promises they are making to the capital&amp;#8217;s 16.8 million people are largely similar.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;An &lt;strong&gt;IndiaSpend&lt;/strong&gt; analysis of the manifestos of &lt;a href="http://www.inc.in/In-Focus/339/Congress-Manifesto-For-Delhi-Election-2015"&gt;Indian National Congress&lt;/a&gt; (INC) and the &lt;a href="http://www.aamaadmiparty.org/AAP-Manifesto-2015.pdf"&gt;Aam Aadmi Party&lt;/a&gt; (AAP) &amp;nbsp;and &amp;#8220;vision document&amp;#8221; of the &lt;a href="http://bjpdelhi.org/files/detail/89"&gt;Bharatiya Janata Party&lt;/a&gt; (BJP) reveal these key issues: reduced power bills and more energy company choices to consumers; more water-supply infrastructure (the AAP&amp;#8217;s trump card here is 700 litres of free water); expanded health and education facilities; enhanced security for women and regularisation of Delhi&amp;#8217;s sprawling unauthorised colonies.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;While development debates for most other states account for rural-urban divides and &amp;#8220;vote banks&amp;#8221; (voting targeted at religious and caste groups), Delhi, one of India&amp;#8217;s largest, most prosperous and unequal urban agglomerations, skips those issues.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;#8220;Development&amp;#8221; for Delhi is not GDP growth but management of urban life.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;This is particularly important because a good urban-development policy for Delhi can become a blueprint for other Indian cities. The effect of the Delhi Metro is one example, as &lt;strong&gt;IndiaSpend&lt;/strong&gt; has previously &lt;a href="http://www.indiaspend.com/cover-story/indias-great-metro-rail-opportunity-40950"&gt;reported&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;The INC is putting forth its 15-year record in power, claiming to have &amp;#8220;made&amp;#8221; Delhi. The BJP has focussed on the central government&amp;#8217;s achievements while making its promises for the capital, and the AAP, which formed the government after the 2013 elections, has stuck to the promises it made last time.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;Let us compare some key issues in the manifestos of these three major parties:&lt;br&gt;&#13;
&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;</value>
    </content>
    <image>&lt;img href='BigFightstable1.jpg' /&gt;</image>
    <width>642</width>
    <height>3305</height>
    <content>
      <value>&lt;p&gt;The urban agenda of all parties is clear, with concrete plans on electricity, water and housing. While electrification is not a concern for the Delhi state government, meeting demand and controlling prices is a big challenge.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;As far as water supply and sanitation is concerned, &lt;a href="http://www.devinfo.org/indiacensuspca/libraries/aspx/Home.aspx"&gt;census&lt;/a&gt; 2011 data reveals that 10% of households in NCT of Delhi are without toilets and 19% of households do not have access to tap water.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Image Credit: &lt;a href="http://www.bjp.org"&gt;BJP.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;br&gt;&#13;
_____________________________________________________________&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;#8220;Liked this story? Indiaspend.org is a non-profit, and we depend on readers like you to drive our public-interest journalism efforts.&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href="http://www.indiaspend.com/donate1" target="_blank"&gt;Donate&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;Rs 500; Rs 1,000, Rs 2,000.&amp;#8221;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
</value>
    </content>
  </article>
</indiaspend>
