<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<indiaspend>
  <article>
    <title>Budget 2014: No Change In Tax Rates, Income Tax Limit Hiked To Rs 2.5 lakh; Full Speech</title>
    <authorname/>
    <date>July 10, 2014</date>
    <category>Politics</category>
    <image>&lt;img href='budget2014coverimage.jpg' /&gt;</image>
    <width>352</width>
    <height>242</height>
    <content>
      <value>Finance Minister Arun Jaitley presented the first Union Budget of the Bharatiya Janata Party (BJP)-led National Democratic Alliance (NDA) by not hiking tax rates and increasing the income tax limit to Rs 2.5 lakh.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;The Finance Minister has promised to meet the fiscal deficit target of 4.1% set by the interim budget, and has set a target of 3.6% in 2015-16. While the direct tax proposals are expected to lead to a loss of Rs 22,000 crore, indirect tax proposals are likely to fetch Rs 7,000 crore for the Government.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Here are some other key highlights:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;Rs 1,000 crore provided for Pradhan Mantri Krishi Sinchayee Yojna.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;Rs 500 crore for Deendayal Upadhyaya Gram Jyoti Yojana.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;AIIMS-like institutions in Andhra Pradesh, West Bengal, Vidarbha in Maharashtra and Poorvanchal in Uttar Pradesh.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;Rs 500 crore for price stabilisation fund to mitigate the risk of price volatility in agriculture produce.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;8,500 km national highway to be constructed in current financial year.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://pib.nic.in/archieve/others/2014/jul/gbEngSpeech.pdf"&gt;Click Here To Read The Full Speech&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;div id="content"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Budget&lt;/b&gt;&lt;b&gt;2014-2015&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Speech&amp;nbsp; of&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;ArunJaitley&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Minister of Finance&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;July 10,&amp;nbsp; 2014&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Madam Speaker&lt;/b&gt;,&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I rise to present the Budget for the year 2014-15.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I.&amp;nbsp; STATE OF THE ECONOMY&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;2.&lt;/b&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; The people of India have decisively voted for a change. The verdict represents the exasperation of the people with the status-quo. India unhesitatingly desires to grow. Those living below the poverty line are anxious to free themselves from the curse of poverty. Those who have got an opportunity to emerge from the difficult challenges have become aspirational. They now want to be a part of the neo middle class. Their next generation has the hunger to use the opportunity that society provides for them. Slow decision making has resulted in a loss of opportunity. Two years of sub five per cent growth in the Indian economy has resulted in a challenging situation. We look forward to lower levels of inflation as compared to the days of double digit rates of food inflation in the last two years. The country is in no mood to suffer unemployment, inadequate basic amenities, lack of infrastructure and apathetic governance.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;3.&lt;/b&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; The slowdown in India broadly reflects the trend in many economies. In contrast to the aftermath of the crisis of 2008-09 when restoration of growth in advanced economies was the primary concern, the continuing slowdown being presently witnessed in many emerging economies has posed a threat to a sustained global recovery. Fortunately, there are green shoots of recovery being seen in the global economy. As per IMF, the world economy is projected to grow at 3.6 per cent in 2014 vis-à-vis 3.0 per cent in 2013, with the Euro area expected to register a positive growth after the contraction witnessed in 2012 and 2013. However, the performance of the US economy with attendant implication for the unconventional monetary policy stance and global financial conditions is pivotal to the fate of global recovery in the coming years. These are the head winds against which the Indian economy would have to maneuver its way to attain high growth trajectory.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;4.&lt;/b&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; As Finance Minister I am duty bound to usher in a policy regime that will result in the desired macro-economic outcome of higher growth, lower inflation, sustained level of external sector balance and a prudent policy stance. The Budget is the most comprehensive action plan in this regard. In the first Budget of this NDA government that I am presenting before the august House, my aim is to lay down a broad policy indicator of the direction in which we wish to take this country. The steps that I will announce in this Budget are only the beginning of a journey towards a sustained growth of 7-8 per cent or above within the next 3-4 years along with macro-economic stabilization that includes lower levels of inflation, lesser fiscal deficit and a manageable current account deficit. Therefore, it would not be wise to expect everything that can be done or must be done to be in the first Budget presented within forty five days of the formation of this Government.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;5.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; &lt;/b&gt;While higher growth is a sine qua non, we cannot be oblivious of the fact that there is a large population of this country which is below the poverty line. It is the poor who suffer the most. We have to ensure that our anti-poverty programs are well targeted.&amp;nbsp; The growing aspirations of the people will be reflected in the development strategy followed by the Government led by the Prime Minister ShriNarendraModi and its mandate of &amp;#8220;Sab kaSaath Sab kaVikas&amp;#8221;. Allow me to assure this House that we have taken up the challenge in the right earnest. We shall leave no stone unturned in creating a vibrant and strong India.&lt;/p&gt;</value>
    </content>
  </article>
</indiaspend>
