<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<indiaspend>
  <article>
    <title> India’s City Slums Can House All Of Italy</title>
    <authorname>Prachi Salve</authorname>
    <date>March 16, 2015</date>
    <category>Politics</category>
    <image>&lt;img href='CitySlumscoverimage.jpg' /&gt;</image>
    <width>1024</width>
    <height>682</height>
    <content>
      <value>&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;It is reasonably well known that 31% of India&amp;#8217;s population, or 377 million out of 1.2 billion people (when last counted in 2011), lived in urban areas.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;div style="width:625px;margin-top:15px"&gt;&lt;div id="InRead"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;What is not as well-known is that nearly 17% of this urban population, or more than 65 million people, lives in slums, a number that has more than doubled over three decades.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;More Indians now live in slums than the number of people in Italy or the UK. The 30-year rise is the equivalent of adding the current population of Canada or Tanzania or two Syrias.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;The&lt;a href="http://www.censusindia.gov.in/2011-Documents/Slum-26-09-13.pdf"&gt; Census&lt;/a&gt; of India defines a slum as a residential area where &amp;#8220;dwellings are unfit for human habitation [due to] dilapidation, overcrowding, faulty arrangements and design of such buildings, narrowness or faulty arrangement of street, lack of ventilation, light, or sanitation facilities or any combination of these factors&amp;#8221;.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;The number of urban poor has fallen 21% over six years, according to poverty &lt;a href="http://planningcommission.nic.in/news/pre_pov2307.pdf"&gt;estimates&lt;/a&gt; of the erstwhile Planning Commission.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;Despite falling poverty, slums have been increasing in cities because they provide housing to millions who are not officially regarded as poor.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;Up to 53 million of 65 million slum-dwellers live below the poverty line, defined as the ability to spend Rs 1,000 for a family of four every month, according to the Planning Commission. The other 12 million belong to what are called &amp;#8220;economically weaker sections&amp;#8221;, with the ability to spend less than Rs 8,000 per family per month.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;Up to 88% of &amp;#8220;economically weaker sections&amp;#8221; and 11% of &amp;#8220;lower-income groups&amp;#8221;, (with the ability to spend between Rs 8,000 to Rs 16,000 per family per month), face housing shortages, according to the &lt;a href="http://www.joneslanglasalle.co.in/india/en-gb/Research/Affordable_Housing_in_India_2012.pdf?27e6f554-2aa8-4864-8bc3-9127a4b902bc"&gt;Ministry&lt;/a&gt; of Housing and Urban Poverty Alleviation.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;The housing shortage is now 19 million units (assuming a family of four, that would be 76 million people without homes and assuming a family of five, 95 million people), according to the ministry.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
</value>
    </content>
    <image>&lt;img href='CitySlumsgraph1.jpg' /&gt;</image>
    <width>610</width>
    <height>335</height>
    <content>
      <value>&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;As more Indians flock to cities, slums proliferate&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;The growth of slums is highest in the five states with the highest urban populations and is correlated with &lt;a href="http://www.indiaspend.com/snapshots/indias-new-urban-misery-housing-poverty"&gt;housing&lt;/a&gt; shortages and urban poverty.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
</value>
    </content>
    <image>&lt;img href='CitySlumsgraph2.jpg' /&gt;</image>
    <width>621</width>
    <height>236</height>
    <content>
      <value>&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;Almost 35% of the urban population in Andhra Pradesh lives in slums, followed by Maharashtra with 24%. So, about one in four Maharashtrian urban dwellers lives in a slum.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;By 2020, India&amp;#8217;s urban population is expected to increase to&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href="http://www.urbanindia.nic.in/programme/uwss/MGI_india_urbanization_fullreport.pdf"&gt;590 million&lt;/a&gt;. The number of towns that reported slums has increased to 2,613 of a total of 4,041 statutory&amp;#8211;or officially defined&amp;#8211;towns of India in 2011, a 50% increase over 10 years.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;Put another way, out of 78.7 million urban households, 13.7 million households live in slums, which is almost 17% of the urban population. Of these 13.7 million households, 38% (5.2 million) live in million-plus cities. The majority stay in one-room houses, with four or more members.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;The government makes estimates of the housing shortage by adding the number of families residing in &amp;#8220;unacceptable (old and dilapidated) houses&amp;#8221;, families residing in &amp;#8220;unacceptable physical and social conditions&amp;#8221; and families without homes.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;There is a clear link between urban poverty, housing shortages and a rising slum population. For example, Maharashtra has the highest slum population (10 million), the second highest number of people below the poverty line and the second-highest housing shortage, of about 1.9 million houses.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;Image Credit: &lt;a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/zeeble/53703600"&gt;Flickr/Sthitaprajna Jena&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;&#13;
__________________________________________________________________________&lt;br&gt;&#13;
&amp;nbsp;&lt;br&gt;&#13;
&lt;em&gt;&amp;#8220;Liked this story? Indiaspend.com is a non-profit, and we depend on readers like you to drive our public-interest journalism efforts. &lt;a href="http://www.indiaspend.com/donate1" target="_blank"&gt;Donate&lt;/a&gt; Rs 500; Rs 1,000, Rs 2,000.&amp;#8221;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
</value>
    </content>
  </article>
</indiaspend>
