<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<indiaspend>
  <article>
    <title>Data: Are Crimes Against Scheduled Castes On An Upswing In India?</title>
    <authorname>Sanjit Oberai</authorname>
    <date>May 30, 2014</date>
    <category>Politics</category>
    <content>
      <value>&lt;p&gt;The gang-rape of two Dalit sisters in Bahun district of Uttar Pradesh not only highlights the atrocities committed against women but also against people belonging to scheduled castes.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;According to &lt;a href=\"http://indiatoday.intoday.in/story/gangrape-murder-badaun-uttar-pradesh-ncw-takes-action/1/364206.html\" target=\"_blank\"&gt;media reports&lt;/a&gt;, the two girls, who were cousins, went missing from their house on Tuesday night. Their bodies were found hanging from a mango tree in the village.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;It has sparked outrage across the country with the National Commission of Women taken suo moto cognisance of the incident.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;This is not the first time such incidents have occurred. IndiaSpend decided to look at cases registered under various crime heads against scheduled castes as per data &lt;a href=\"http://ncrb.nic.in/CD-CII2012/Additional_Tables_CII_2012/Additional%20Tables.htm\" target=\"_blank\"&gt;compiled &lt;/a&gt;by the National Crime Records Bureau, and here are the points.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;The data set has been broken into ten segments starting from murder, rape, kidnapping &amp;amp; abduction, dacoity, robbery, arson etc (refer table below) and is over the period 2001-2012.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;The data we are looking at is for rape cases, which are up 20% to 1,576 cases in 2012 from 1,316 cases in 2001. Rape cases accounted for 4.7% of total crimes against scheduled castes in 2012.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;Kidnapping &amp;amp; abduction and &amp;#8220;other crimes against SCs&amp;#8221; are the two heads which have increased 23% &amp;nbsp;and 16% , respectively in a decade.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;</value>
    </content>
    <image>&lt;img href='dalitcrimes.jpg' /&gt;</image>
    <width>661</width>
    <height>620</height>
  </article>
</indiaspend>
