<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<indiaspend>
  <article>
    <title>Why A $20-Billion Defence Deal May Be Scrapped</title>
    <authorname>Abheet Singh Sethi</authorname>
    <date>February 5, 2015</date>
    <category>Defence</category>
    <image>&lt;img href='DefenceDealcoverimage.jpg' /&gt;</image>
    <width>620</width>
    <height>427</height>
    <content>
      <value>&lt;div style="font-size: 12px;"&gt;The fighter jet in question, the Rafale from Dassault.&lt;/div&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;A $20-billion (Rs 1,20,000 crore) defence deal with French aerospace major Dassault may be unravelling, thanks to a change in thinking by Defence Minister Manohar Parrikar.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;Parikkar recently &lt;a href="http://www.business-standard.com/article/current-affairs/rafale-in-storm-clouds-parrikar-says-iaf-can-make-do-with-sukhoi-30s-114123100706_1.html"&gt;hinted&lt;/a&gt; that the deal for Rafale medium multi-role combat aircraft (MMRCA), under negotiation with Dassault since 2012, might be scrapped. He further said that additional Sukhoi-30 MKI fighters, built by Hindustan Aeronautics (HAL) at its Nashik plant, could substitute for them.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;The Sukhoi-30 MKI is currently India&amp;#8217;s most advanced air fighter and forms the backbone of its air power. It&amp;#8217;s also half the current cost of a Rafale. However, delays from HAL have slowed its entry into the Indian Air Force (IAF).&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;Air Vice Marshal (Rtd) Manmohan Bahadur, Distinguished Fellow at Centre for Air Power Studies, New Delhi, told &lt;strong&gt;IndiaSpend&lt;/strong&gt; the statement of the minister could be taken as a statement of intent.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;#8220;A lot of operational issues will have to be taken into account before such a decision is taken,&amp;#8221; said Bahadur, &amp;#8220;the two aircraft are of a different class, requiring different types of infrastructure and aircrew&amp;#8212;two for the Sukhoi instead of one for the Rafale, so training requirements double.&amp;#8221;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;</value>
    </content>
    <image>&lt;img href='DefenceDealtable1.jpg' /&gt;</image>
    <width>642</width>
    <height>258</height>
    <content>
      <value>&lt;p&gt;IAF first &lt;a href="http://www.saiindia.gov.in/english/home/Our_Products/Audit_Report/Government_Wise/union_audit/recent_reports/union_compliance/2014/Defence/Report_35/overview.pdf"&gt;signed a deal&lt;/a&gt; with the Russian government to purchase eight air defence Su-30K and 32 multi-role Su-30 MK aircraft in 1996. IAF bought an additional 10 Su-30 MKs in December 1998.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;The original contract signed in 1996 also envisaged the development of new Su-30 MKI aircraft by integrating the Russian Su-30MK with the latest western, Russian and indigenous avionics. These were to be indigenously manufactured by HAL under a licence from Russian defence export agency Rosoboronexport.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;India and Russia agreed to the licensed production of 140 Su-30 MKI aircraft, 920 engines and 140 sets of airborne equipment. These aircraft were to be delivered by HAL in four phases by 2017-18. However, in March 2006, the Ministry of Defence advanced the delivery of these aircraft to 2014-15 to counter a sharp fall in combat aircraft available, due to crashes and obsolescence.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;The IAF then placed an additional order for 82 aircraft with HAL, taking the total number of indigenously produced aircraft to 222, to be &lt;a href="http://www.business-standard.com/article/current-affairs/air-force-likely-to-get-entire-sukhoi-30mki-fleet-by-2019-114042200138_1.html"&gt;delivered&lt;/a&gt; between 2002-03 and 2016-17. No more than &lt;a href="http://www.hal-india.com/HAL%20Hands-over/ND__94"&gt;150&lt;/a&gt; aircraft have been delivered.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;The central government&amp;#8217;s auditor, the Comptroller and Auditor General (CAG) was &lt;a href="http://www.saiindia.gov.in/english/home/Our_Products/Audit_Report/Government_Wise/union_audit/recent_reports/union_compliance/2014/Defence/Report_35/chap_9.pdf"&gt;less than impressed&lt;/a&gt;, noting delays in technology transfers from Russia.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;The delivery schedule of 222 aircraft has been pushed back by two-and-half years to &lt;a href="http://www.business-standard.com/article/current-affairs/air-force-likely-to-get-entire-sukhoi-30mki-fleet-by-2019-114042200138_1.html"&gt;2019&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Crisis on the frontline&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;The IAF now has 25 active fighter squadrons (16-18 aircraft each) instead of 42, according &lt;a href="http://164.100.47.134/lsscommittee/Defence/16_Defence_4.pdf"&gt;to a recent report&lt;/a&gt; tabled by the Parliamentary Standing Committee on Defence.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;Of these 25 squadrons, 14 use MiG-21 and MiG-27 aircraft, set to retire between 2015 and 2024. The report further states that the IAF requires &amp;#8220;at least 45 squadrons to counter a two-front (Pakistan and China) collusive threat&amp;#8221;.&amp;nbsp; This is why the MMRCA from Dassault and the home-built Tejas light combat aircraft were important.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;The MMRCA was first &lt;a href="http://www.newindianexpress.com/nation/article389709.ece?service=print"&gt;envisaged&lt;/a&gt; by IAF in 2000 as a stop-gap arrangement to replace the vintage Mig-21 aircraft, due to delays with the Tejas. In 2007, a &lt;a href="http://pib.nic.in/newsite/erelease.aspx?relid=30522"&gt;Request for Proposal&lt;/a&gt; (RFP) was issued for 126 MMRCA at an estimated cost of Rs 42,000 crore ($12 billion).&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;Since 2012, the defence ministry and Dassault have not been able to close the MMRCA deal. A key reason is that Dassault is unwilling to guarantee the quality of 108 fighters to be manufactured in India.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;The second reason is the escalation in costs by &lt;a href="http://www.dnaindia.com/india/report-dna-exclusive-100-price-escalation-on-rafale-fighter-aircraft-to-rs-175-lakh-crore-likely-to-dent-iaf-s-strike-capability-1957107"&gt; 100%&lt;/a&gt;. A recent &lt;a href="http://www.dnaindia.com/india/report-dna-exclusive-100-price-escalation-on-rafale-fighter-aircraft-to-rs-175-lakh-crore-likely-to-dent-iaf-s-strike-capability-1957107"&gt;report&lt;/a&gt; said that the technology transfer agreement and the Indian assembly line had led to the costs sky-rocketing to around Rs 1,20,000 crore ($20 billion).&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;As &lt;a href="http://www.business-standard.com/article/current-affairs/rafale-in-storm-clouds-parrikar-says-iaf-can-make-do-with-sukhoi-30s-114123100706_1.html"&gt;Parrikar&lt;/a&gt; said, the cost of a Rafale has now ballooned to twice that of the IAF&amp;#8217;s primary workhorse, the Sukhoi 30 MKI.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;Can Parrikar&amp;#8217;s Plan B work?&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;Air Vice Marshal Bahadur feels HAL&amp;#8217;s track record does not inspire confidence. &amp;#8220;HAL will have to raise new infrastructure to take on the numbers required,&amp;#8221; he said.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;The bottom line: the IAF will remain a weakened force unless the jet mess can be sorted out.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;_____________________________________________________________&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;#8220;Liked this story? Indiaspend.org is a non-profit, and we depend on readers like you to drive our public-interest journalism efforts.&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href="http://www.indiaspend.com/donate1" target="_blank"&gt;Donate&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;Rs 500; Rs 1,000, Rs 2,000.&amp;#8221;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
</value>
    </content>
  </article>
</indiaspend>
