<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<indiaspend>
  <article>
    <title>How To Cut Your—And India’s—Electricity Bills</title>
    <authorname>IndiaSpend Team</authorname>
    <date>January 10, 2015</date>
    <category>Politics</category>
    <image>&lt;img href='ElectricityBillscoverimage.jpg' /&gt;</image>
    <width>620</width>
    <height>399</height>
    <content>
      <value>&lt;p&gt;We may soon have to get used to seeing more&amp;nbsp;LED&amp;nbsp;bulbs in our homes and streets now with the government adopting a new&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href="http://pib.nic.in/newsite/PrintRelease.aspx?relid=114328"&gt;programme&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;to promote their use. With the Prime Minister&amp;#8217;s backing, the National Programme for LED-based Home and Street Lighting will look to replace normal, incandescent bulbs that are widely used with more energy-efficient&amp;nbsp;LED&amp;nbsp;bulbs.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;#8220;26 billion kWh (kilo-Watt-hours) of energy can be saved every year if all 77 crore incandescent bulbs sold in India are converted to&amp;nbsp;LEDs&amp;#8221;,&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/PiyushGoyal/status/552092275837128704"&gt;tweeted&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;Piyush Goyal, Minister of State with Independent Charge for Power, Coal and New &amp;amp; Renewable Energy. He also&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/PiyushGoyal/status/552091386413981697"&gt;tweeted&lt;/a&gt;, &amp;#8220;(Putting&amp;nbsp;LED&amp;nbsp;bulbs in) 3 crore street lights in the country has the potential of saving 5 billion kWh every year, which would result in cost savings of Rs. 3,000 crore!&amp;#8221;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;LED&amp;nbsp;bulbs are quite expensive, though, with retail prices at least 15 times that of an incandescent bulb, though a government scheme has been &lt;a href="http://pib.nic.in/newsite/PrintRelease.aspx?relid=114328"&gt;introduced&lt;/a&gt; in Delhi to provide&amp;nbsp;LED&amp;nbsp;bulbs to the public at a lower cost of Rs 130. Apart from how energy-efficient&amp;nbsp;LED&amp;nbsp;bulbs are, they also last much longer than incandescent bulbs, as much as 16 times longer.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;However, the main competition for&amp;nbsp;LED&amp;nbsp;bulbs comes not from incandescent bulbs but from CFL bulbs. These, however, aren&amp;#8217;t very environment-friendly. CFL bulbs contain the toxic chemical&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href="http://www.business-standard.com/article/economy-policy/standard-for-mercury-level-checking-in-cfl-lamp-formulated-bis-111100300055_1.html"&gt;mercury&lt;/a&gt;, which could be released into the environment if you don&amp;#8217;t dispose of them properly.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;If anyone was ever confused about the kind of bulb they should use, the infographic below shows how the choice has never been clearer.&lt;/p&gt;</value>
    </content>
    <image>&lt;img href='ElectricityBillsimage1.jpg' /&gt;</image>
    <width>646</width>
    <height>1721</height>
    <content>
      <value>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Image Credit:&lt;a href="http://www.dreamstime.com/stock-image-led-bulb-eco-concept-glowing-image36661531"&gt;Dreamstime.com|Choneschones&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;_____________________________________________________________&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;#8220;Liked this story? Indiaspend.org is a non-profit, and we depend on readers like you to drive our public-interest journalism efforts. &lt;a href="http://www.indiaspend.com/donate1"&gt;Donate&lt;/a&gt; Rs 500; Rs 1,000, Rs 2,000.&amp;#8221;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
</value>
    </content>
  </article>
</indiaspend>
