<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<indiaspend>
  <article>
    <title>Jobs Decline In India’s Biggest Employment Arena</title>
    <authorname>Prachi Salve</authorname>
    <date>January 17, 2015</date>
    <category>Politics</category>
    <image>&lt;img href='EmploymentArenacoverimage.jpg' /&gt;</image>
    <width>620</width>
    <height>373</height>
    <content>
      <value>&lt;p&gt;Employment in the informal sector, the biggest provider of jobs in India, has declined 6% from 2004-05, according to government data.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;Coming on the heels of a &lt;a href="http://www.indiaspend.com/cover-story/modis-big-make-in-india-problem-fewer-factory-jobs-79711"&gt;Indiaspend report&lt;/a&gt; of a slowdown in formal-sector factory jobs, this is a disquieting trend because the informal sector provides employment to 72% of India&amp;#8217;s workforce.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;These are also very vulnerable people because the majority receive no social security, health insurance or related benefits&amp;#8212;and nine of ten workers do not even have written contracts.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;About 340 million of a total of 472 million people found jobs in the informal sector at the end of 2011-12. Roughly 12 million Indians seek jobs every year, but no more than 11.6 million find employment.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;At the all-India level, nearly 78% of the total workforce was employed in the informal sector in 2004-2005 while the proportion was about 71% in 2009-10 and about 72% in 2011-12.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;The informal sector consists of proprietary and partnership enterprises (excluding those run by non-corporate entities such as co-operatives, trusts and non-profit institutions), in the non-agricultural sector and agriculture-related activities, excluding crop production, according to the &lt;a href="http://mospi.nic.in/Mospi_New/upload/nss_report_557_26aug14.pdf"&gt;latest report&lt;/a&gt; by the National Sample Survey Organisation of the Ministry of Statistics and Programme Implementation.&lt;/p&gt;</value>
    </content>
    <image>&lt;img href='EmploymentArenagraph1.jpg' /&gt;</image>
    <width>582</width>
    <height>351</height>
    <content>
      <value>&lt;p&gt;Within the informal sector, the non-agriculture sector employed about 86% of informal workers in rural areas and 98% in urban areas. The non-agriculture sector employed 95% of urban females and 99% of urban males, and so is the biggest employer. In rural areas, the sector employed 94% of males and 63% of females.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;This reveals that the non-agriculture sector is increasingly providing employment, especially to men,in rural areas.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;The non-agriculture sectors that provided the most jobs were manufacturing, &lt;a href="http://www.indiaspend.com/investigations/how-indias-construction-workers-get-gypped-of-their-due-51414"&gt;construction&lt;/a&gt;, wholesale and retail trade, transportation and storage.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
</value>
    </content>
    <image>&lt;img href='EmploymentArenagraph2.jpg' /&gt;</image>
    <width>576</width>
    <height>324</height>
    <image>&lt;img href='EmploymentArenagraph3.jpg' /&gt;</image>
    <width>534</width>
    <height>350</height>
    <content>
      <value>&lt;p&gt;Manufacturing and construction in the rural areas provided the most jobs. While construction provided the most employment to rural males, manufacturing employed nearly 36% women in rural areas during 2011-12.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;In urban areas, retail provided the highest employment in the informal sector with 28%, followed closely by manufacturing. It also provided the highest employment among urban males(31%), while manufacturing provided the highest employment for urban females (43%).&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Written contracts.Pensions.Health insurance. What are those?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;Most workers in the informal sector do not enjoy any benefits, with casual labourers among the most exploited&amp;#8212;Almost 97% work without a written contract, and 93% do not have social-security benefits, such as pensions or health insurance.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
</value>
    </content>
    <image>&lt;img href='EmploymentArenagraph4.jpg' /&gt;</image>
    <width>528</width>
    <height>340</height>
    <content>
      <value>&lt;p&gt;Let us look at the sector-wise data on benefits offered to informal workers.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
</value>
    </content>
    <image>&lt;img href='EmploymentArenagraph5.jpg' /&gt;</image>
    <width>561</width>
    <height>325</height>
    <image>&lt;img href='EmploymentArenagraph6.jpg' /&gt;</image>
    <width>538</width>
    <height>341</height>
    <content>
      <value>&lt;p&gt;Construction seems to be the worst employer in rural areas; more than half the employees enjoy almost no benefits. In urban areas, more than a quarter of informal sector employees enjoy almost no benefits in manufacturing industries.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;As C.P Chandrasekhar, economist and professor at Jawaharlal Nehru University (JNU) pointed &lt;a href="http://www.thehindu.com/opinion/columns/Chandrasekhar/indias-informal-economy/article6375902.ece"&gt;out&lt;/a&gt;:&amp;nbsp; &amp;#8220;When approached from the employment side, non-formal employment still constitutes an overwhelmingly large proportion of employment, outside of crop production in India. This questions the grounds on which the need for labour reform is often defended.&amp;#8221;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;The discrimination against women is evident.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;The average salary per day was about Rs. 258 per day for men in the informal sector in urban areas. Women got Rs 194.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;In rural areas, men got Rs 189 per day, while women got Rs 121.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;IndiaSpend had &lt;a href="http://www.indiaspend.com/cover-story/modis-big-make-in-india-problem-fewer-factory-jobs-79711"&gt;reported&lt;/a&gt; that while Prime Minister Narendra Modi pushes his Make-in-India manufacturing plan and factory output rebounds, new data indicate two disquieting trends. One, there is a slowdown in employment in the formal, organised sector (which in any case employs only 12% of India&amp;#8217;s labour force), the prime staging ground of Modi&amp;#8217;s programme. More than 400,000 people lost their jobs during the financial year 2012-13, according to government data. Two, this slowdown hides a larger, long-term trend: India Inc is automating and squeezing more output from its workers and so needs fewer of them.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;______________________________________________________________&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;#8220;Liked this story? Indiaspend.org is a non-profit, and we depend on readers like you to drive our public-interest journalism efforts.&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href="http://www.indiaspend.com/donate1" target="_blank"&gt;Donate&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;Rs 500; Rs 1,000, Rs 2,000.&amp;#8221;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
</value>
    </content>
  </article>
</indiaspend>
