<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<indiaspend>
  <article>
    <title>A Farmer’s Life Crisis—And India’s Farming Predicament</title>
    <authorname>Bhasker Tripathi, Gaon Connection, </authorname>
    <date>April 16, 2015</date>
    <category>Politics</category>
    <image>&lt;img href='FarmingPredicamentcoverimage.jpg' /&gt;</image>
    <width>620</width>
    <height>465</height>
    <content>
      <value>&lt;p style="font-size: 12px;margin-left:5px;"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Ramlal, 35, of UP&amp;#8217;s Rajwada village, could not escape the effects of India&amp;#8217;s increasingly uncertain weather, despite being part of India&amp;#8217;s farming elite and its middle class. His wheat farm has been devastated, and government compensation does not cover even 13% of his losses. &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Image:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; Bhasker Tripathi, Gaon Connection&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rajwada (Uttar Pradesh)/ Mumbai&lt;/strong&gt;: Lean, intense and troubled, pea-and-wheat farmer Ramlal is not supposed to be in crisis.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;div style="width:625px;margin-top:15px"&gt;&lt;div id="InRead"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;At 35, Ramlal (he uses only one name), is part of India&amp;#8217;s farming elite&amp;#8212;the &lt;a href="http://pib.nic.in/newsite/PrintRelease.aspx?relid=113778"&gt;19%&lt;/a&gt; that owns more than 1.1 hectare of land&amp;#8212;and a rural representative of India&amp;#8217;s booming middle class. He owns 21 hectares of land (5 hectares sown with peas), a television, motorcycle and tractor, and lives with his family of eight in a four-room brick house, with a courtyard and store, in a south-western corner of Uttar Pradesh (UP), a state that accounts for a &lt;a href="http://pib.nic.in/newsite/PrintRelease.aspx?relid=113796"&gt;fifth&lt;/a&gt; of India&amp;#8217;s farming households.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;Yet, after unseasonal rains and hailstorms ravaged his winter, or &lt;em&gt;rabi&lt;/em&gt;, wheat crop, the economic crisis upon him indicates the tenuous situation of the Indian farmer, poor or relatively prosperous, even when the government provides compensation.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;#8220;It is as good as nothing,&amp;#8221; said Ramlal, of the Rs 36,000 he will get as compensation from the UP government.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;To understand why, we jotted down his agricultural expenses:&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
</value>
    </content>
    <image>&lt;img href='FarmingPredicamentgraph1.jpg' /&gt;</image>
    <width>518</width>
    <height>263</height>
    <content>
      <value>&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;Ramlal spent nearly Rs 17,500 per hectare of wheat, so the official compensation of Rs 18,000 per hectare appears to cover his expenses&amp;#8212;except that the government allows compensation for a maximum of two hectares. Ramlal lost crops across 16 hectares of land.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;If this was a normal year, Ramlal would have sold his harvest to the state-owned Food Corporation of India for (roughly) Rs 58,000 per hectare, a profit of Rs 30,500 per hectare (without transportation cost). So, in good years, Ramlal prospered, but increasingly uncertain weather&amp;#8212;as we shall see later&amp;#8212;has upset a tenuous normalcy across rural north India.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;Ramlal&amp;#8217;s total losses are Rs 2,80,000, the state reimbursement covering less than 13% of crop-raising costs.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
</value>
    </content>
    <image>&lt;img href='FarmingPredicamentgraph2.jpg' /&gt;</image>
    <width>524</width>
    <height>132</height>
    <content>
      <value>&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;From satellites, from the ground&amp;#8212;the estimation problem&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;Ramlal did not lose all his wheat. He estimated that 10% of the crop could be saved. A government estimate put that figure at 30%&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;It is hard to assess what the remnant might fetch. Ramlal said the harvested kernels were blackened and stunted, which means lower rates.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;Like &lt;a href="http://www.newindianexpress.com/nation/Less-Than-20-Percent-Farmers-Have-Crop-Insurance-Study/2015/04/12/article2760858.ece"&gt;80%&lt;/a&gt; of Indian farmers, Ramlal does not have crop insurance, an agricultural dysfunction that leaves governments liable&amp;#8212;not by law but by political necessity. At least &lt;a href="http://www.thehindu.com/opinion/columns/sainath/over-2000-fewer-farmers-every-day/article4674190.ece"&gt;600 million&lt;/a&gt; Indians still depend on farming, although the share of agriculture in India&amp;#8217;s gross domestic farmers is &lt;a href="http://planningcommission.nic.in/data/datatable/data_2312/DatabookDec2014%2043.pdf"&gt;declining&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;Farmers are an electoral constituency that cannot be ignored and could, as this &lt;em&gt;Livemint&lt;/em&gt; report &lt;a href="http://www.livemint.com/Politics/JLkYB6Tc6LjcAbVZwqgoCM/Unseasonal-rains-deepen-distress-and-debt-on-farms.html"&gt;warned&lt;/a&gt;, imperil the Bharatiya Janata Party.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;Prime Minister Narendra Modi &lt;a href="http://www.livemint.com/Politics/HCmLrN18OwiBMfHB83QNUL/Govt-promises-higher-compensation-for-farmers-hit-by-unseaso.html"&gt;promised&lt;/a&gt; an increase in compensation and dispatched senior ministers to visit farms in 14 states. One of those, Nitin Gadkari, recently &lt;a href="http://ibnlive.in.com/news/dont-rely-on-god-or-government-nitin-gadkari-tells-farmers/539138-3-237.html"&gt;advised&lt;/a&gt; farmers against relying on &amp;#8220;God or government&amp;#8221;.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;#8220;You, yourselves, are the architect of your lives,&amp;#8221; said Gadkari.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;div style="margin-left:100px;margin-right:100px;"&gt;&lt;iframe width="420" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/24RuWKQF020" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em style="margin-left:102px;font-size: 11px;"&gt;Source: India News&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;Currently, Ramlal&amp;#8217;s only concern is how the government assesses his crop losses.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;There are two ways of establishing such losses, said Sudhir Panwar, a member of UP&amp;#8217;s Planning Commission:&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&#13;
&amp;#8212;One, by satellites that pass over an area and use special sensors and cameras to determine damage in fields. &lt;a href="http://www.downtoearth.org.in/node/30386"&gt;Remote sensing&lt;/a&gt;, as the technique is called, is reasonably accurate but only offers a block- or &lt;em&gt;taluk&lt;/em&gt;-level view.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&#13;
&amp;#8212;Two, a subjective assessment by the local &lt;em&gt;Lekhpal&lt;/em&gt;, the local revenue officer. These assessments may be an easier method of reaching individual farmers, but they are greatly inaccurate.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;UP and 13 other states hit by the recent crisis largely depend on the &lt;em&gt;lekhpal&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;#8220;Obviously, this involves huge amounts of guesswork,&amp;#8221; said Himanshu (he uses only one name), an agricultural economist from Delhi&amp;#8217;s Jawaharlal Nehru University. &amp;#8220;Revenue officials are hardly equipped to assess the damage and there are very few of them to take care of large geographical areas.&amp;#8221;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;The result is &amp;#8220;guesstimates&amp;#8221;, said Himanshu. &amp;#8220;That is why there are so many flip-flops (sic), as far as these estimates are concerned.&amp;#8221;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;In Delhi, on March 24, 2015, the agriculture ministry &lt;a href="http://www.livemint.com/Politics/HCmLrN18OwiBMfHB83QNUL/Govt-promises-higher-compensation-for-farmers-hit-by-unseaso.html"&gt;estimated&lt;/a&gt; that crops on 18 million hectares&amp;#8212;about 30% of the rabi crop&amp;#8212;were damaged. Two days later, this was reduced to nearly 11 million hectares.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
</value>
    </content>
    <image>&lt;img href='FarmingPredicamentgraph3.jpg' /&gt;</image>
    <width>516</width>
    <height>240</height>
    <content>
      <value>&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;In UP, the number of districts declared affected by heavy rains and hail has increased from 33 to 40, officials told &lt;strong&gt;Gaon Connection&lt;/strong&gt;. The estimated losses have increased from Rs 744 crore to Rs 1,100 crore.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;About half a million farmers have been affected, and 35 have committed suicide, which the government, as &lt;strong&gt;Gaon Connection&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;IndiaSpend&lt;/strong&gt; previously &lt;a href="http://www.indiaspend.com/cover-story/as-farmers-kill-themselves-uttar-pradesh-hides-deaths-54127"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;reported&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, is reluctant to admit as being related to the farm crisis.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The unpredictable weather and agriculture&amp;#8217;s dwindling fortunes&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;What the government will admit is that increasingly unpredictable weather will continue to imperil farmers like Ramlal.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;Lalitpur, the district that hosts Ramlal&amp;#8217;s village of Rajwada, suffered unseasonal rain in 2014 as well. As the chart below shows, the variations over three years have been severe:&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
</value>
    </content>
    <image>&lt;img href='FarmingPredicamentgraph4.jpg' /&gt;</image>
    <width>654</width>
    <height>673</height>
    <content>
      <value>&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;The data show how excess rainfall relates to crop damage.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;For instance, Eastern Rajasthan, the desert state&amp;#8217;s farm belt, had more than 14 times the normal rainfall this pre-monsoon season.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;IndiaSpend&lt;/strong&gt;&amp;#8217;s&amp;nbsp;previous reports on &lt;a href="http://www.indiaspend.com/cover-story/food-security-act-good-move-but-yields-low-global-agri-body-43599"&gt;yields&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;and&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href="http://www.indiaspend.com/special-reports/indias-50-year-old-agri-challenge-low-foodgrain-per-capita-budget-2014-primer-63440"&gt;food security&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;make it clear that farms depend too much on increasingly uncertain rainfall: while there wasn&amp;#8217;t enough rain during the pre-monsoon&amp;nbsp;&lt;em&gt;kharif&lt;/em&gt;&amp;nbsp;season (July-October) last year, there has been vastly excess rainfall during this &lt;em&gt;rabi&lt;/em&gt;&amp;nbsp;season (October-March).&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;Agriculture&amp;#8217;s fortunes are linked to&amp;#8212;and affect&amp;#8212;India&amp;#8217;s economy, but as the chart below shows, India&amp;#8217;s economy in general is doing much better than its agricultural sector, which is gripped by low growth and low output.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
</value>
    </content>
    <image>&lt;img href='FarmingPredicamentgraph5.jpg' /&gt;</image>
    <width>527</width>
    <height>268</height>
    <content>
      <value>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The last&amp;#8212;and, increasingly, first&amp;#8212;resort, loans&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;Back in Rajwada village, Ramlal&amp;#8212;considering his future&amp;#8212;reluctantly admitted to another problem: unpaid bank loans.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;Uncomfortable talking about loans, as the relatively prosperous tend to be, Ramlal said he took a loan in October last year, during the sowing season. He would not say how much he borrowed.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;He has no savings to repay these loans.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;#8220;I will have to get a fresh loan for the next cropping season,&amp;#8221; said Ramlal, now part of the &lt;a href="http://pib.nic.in/newsite/PrintRelease.aspx?relid=113796"&gt;52%&lt;/a&gt; of indebted Indian farming households. Since banks do not allow new loans until previous debts are repaid, Ramlal&amp;#8212;although he did not admit it&amp;#8212;might end up at a moneylender.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;Ramlal said he would pull together what he can from &amp;#8220;all sources&amp;#8221;.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;More forthcoming was a poorer Rajwada farmer, Dev Joo, 90, whom we revisited from a &lt;a href="http://www.indiaspend.com/cover-story/as-farmers-kill-themselves-uttar-pradesh-hides-deaths-54127"&gt;previous&lt;/a&gt; &lt;strong&gt;Gaon Connection&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;IndiaSpend&lt;/strong&gt; story.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;Joo took a loan of Rs 9,000 on his &lt;em&gt;Kisaan&lt;/em&gt; (farmer&amp;#8217;s) credit card but he could not make repayments because of successive crop losses. He now owes the bank Rs 18,000, including interest. Joo could go to a moneylender, but that means the cycle of debt will continue.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
</value>
    </content>
    <image>&lt;img href='FarmingPredicamentimage1.jpg' /&gt;</image>
    <width>467</width>
    <height>350</height>
    <content>
      <value>&lt;p style="font-size: 12px;margin-left:80px;margin-right:430px;width:457px;"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Dev Joo, 90, faces life as a labourer, after rain and hailstorms destroyed his wheat crop in UP&amp;#8217;s Rajwada village. With no money to repay a Rs-18,000 debt on his farmer&amp;#8217;s credit card, Joo mulls going to a moneylender and joining nearly 40 million Indian farmers who abandoned farming and, over a decade, became labourers. &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Image:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; Bhasker Tripathi, Gaon Connection&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;Joo&amp;#8217;s only solution is to work as a labourer, a situation that millions of farmers are forced into, something that he is preparing himself for.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;As the livelihoods of more than half of all Indians living on farm incomes decline, &lt;a href="http://mospi.nic.in/Mospi_New/site/home.aspx"&gt;government data&lt;/a&gt; show that about 9 million people quit cultivation between 2001 and 2011, and the number of agricultural labourers grew by 38 million.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;#8220;&lt;em&gt;Mazdoori karke poora karenge, aur kya karen?&lt;/em&gt; (I will do manual labour and repay my debts, what else to do?),&amp;#8221; said Joo.  But such labour does not pay more than Rs 150 per day, and there aren&amp;#8217;t that many opportunities in Lalitpur.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;As for Ramlal, becoming a labourer is not something he would like to contemplate.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;(&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tripathi&lt;/strong&gt; is Senior Reporter at &lt;a href="http://www.gaonconnection.com/"&gt;Gaon Connection&lt;/a&gt;, a rural newspaper published in Hindi from Lucknow. &lt;strong&gt;Tewari&lt;/strong&gt; is an analyst with IndiaSpend.&lt;/em&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
</value>
    </content>
    <image>&lt;img href='FarmingPredicamentimage2.jpg' /&gt;</image>
    <width>500</width>
    <height>167</height>
    <content>
      <value>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Update:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;This story has been modified to reflect the change in compensation loss for farmers.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br&gt;&#13;
__________________________________________________________________________&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;#8220;Liked this story? Indiaspend.com is a non-profit, and we depend on readers like you to drive our public-interest journalism efforts. &lt;a href="http://www.indiaspend.com/donate1" target="_blank"&gt;Donate&lt;/a&gt; Rs 500; Rs 1,000, Rs 2,000.&amp;#8221;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
</value>
    </content>
  </article>
</indiaspend>
