<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<indiaspend>
  <article>
    <title>Fact Check: Is India The World’s 2nd Fastest Growing Economy?</title>
    <authorname>Prachi Salve </authorname>
    <date>April 11, 2014</date>
    <category>Economy</category>
    <content>
      <value>&lt;p&gt;The communications adviser to the Prime Minister&amp;#8217;s Office, put out a tweet on 9th April, which claimed that &amp;#8220;India is the second fastest growing economy in the world since 2004&amp;#8243;.&lt;br&gt;&#13;
An accompanying chart showed that India grew at an average growth rate of 7.28% during the period 2004-2014. The tweet obviously attracted a lot of attention with some accusing him of using manipulated data, etc.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;</value>
    </content>
    <image>&lt;img href='pankaj.jpg' /&gt;</image>
    <width>491</width>
    <height>582</height>
    <content>
      <value>&lt;p&gt;We decided to check the data available with the International Monetary Fund (IMF), and here is what we found. The data used by Pachauri seems to be from a report written by IMF economist Juan Yépez who has used a specific set of countries in his report titled: &amp;#8220;Spillover Feature: Should Advanced Economies Worry about Growth Shocks in Emerging Market Economies?&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;The report analyses the impact on advanced economies of growth shocks emanating from emerging markets, which ask questions like &amp;#8220;How much would a widespread growth shock in emerging market economies today affect advanced economies&amp;#8217; output growth?&amp;#8221;, among other questions.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;The IMF report looked at a specific set of countries &amp;#8211; France, Germany, Italy, Spain, U.K., U.S, Argentina, Brazil, Chile, China, Colombia, India, Indonesia, Malaysia, Mexico, Philippines, Poland, Russia, South Africa, Thailand and Turkey. If we look at data using only these countries, Pachauri&amp;#8217;s tweet is correct.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;However, if we look at the overall global growth of countries, the chart uploaded by him can be misleading. If we took the average of growth during 2004-2014, India does not feature among the fastest growing countries. The fastest growing country is Qatar (13.49%) followed by Azerbaijan (12.19%) and Turkmenistan 11.49%), which are much smaller economies. Here, India ranks 21st on the list with an average growth rate of 7.27%.&lt;/p&gt;</value>
    </content>
    <image>&lt;img href='pankaj2.jpg' /&gt;</image>
    <width>846</width>
    <height>775</height>
  </article>
</indiaspend>
