<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<indiaspend>
  <article>
    <title>Budget 2014: Costing India’s Flagship Programmes</title>
    <authorname>Pranav Garimella </authorname>
    <date>February 17, 2014</date>
    <category>Politics</category>
    <image>&lt;img href='flagshipcoverimage.jpg' /&gt;</image>
    <width>303</width>
    <height>168</height>
    <content>
      <value>IndiaSpend looks at the 2014-2015 union budget to catalogue the Government&amp;#8217;s top five flagship programmes. Many of these programmes draw criticism for their faulty design &amp;amp; less-than-effective implementation. Nevertheless, these programmes have helped the Government focus efforts in a manner that would have otherwise been difficult to achieve.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;India&amp;#8217;s single largest flagship programme is the Mahatma Gandhi National Rural Employment Guarantee popularly referred as MGNREGA or NREGA. The Government has allocated Rs 34,000 crore for 2014-15, marginally higher than Rs 33,000 crore allocated during the previous year to provide guaranteed employment to almost 50 million rural households.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;Under the National Rural Drinking Water Programme (NRDWP), Rs. 11,000 crore has been allocated in 2014-15, an increase of 13.4% from the revised estimates of the previous year.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;National Rural Health Mission (NRHM) was not allocated any funds in the interim budget for 2014-15 while the revised estimates for 2013-14 stood at Rs. 9, 620 crore.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;Jawaharlal Nehru National Urban Renewal Mission (JnNURM) was allocated Rs 7, 060 crore under the interim budget for 2014-15 while the revised estimates for 2013-14 was Rs 37.75 crore. It is to be noted that the scheme has almost run its course and was supposed to be terminated in 2012-13 but was extended by a year, which can possibly explain the under utilisation of funds under the programme.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;Click&lt;a href="http://www.indiaspend.com/latest-headlines/budget-2014-costing-indias-flagship-programmes-46546"&gt; here&lt;/a&gt; for more.&lt;/p&gt;</value>
    </content>
    <image>&lt;img href='flagshiptable1.jpg' /&gt;</image>
    <width>623</width>
    <height>735</height>
  </article>
</indiaspend>
