<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<indiaspend>
  <article>
    <title>1 Laboratory For 88 Million, As India Faces Food-Safety Crisis</title>
    <authorname>Chaitanya Mallapur</authorname>
    <date>April 7, 2015</date>
    <category>Politics</category>
    <image>&lt;img href='FoodSafetycoverimage.jpg' /&gt;</image>
    <width>620</width>
    <height>412</height>
    <content>
      <value>&lt;p&gt;Facing a growing food- and water-contamination crisis, India has only 148 &lt;a href="http://164.100.47.132/LssNew/psearch/QResult16.aspx?qref=12177"&gt;food-testing&lt;/a&gt; laboratories. In other words, each laboratory serves 88 million people.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;div style="width:625px;margin-top:15px"&gt;&lt;div id="InRead"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Maharashtra has the most laboratories, 27, a laboratory for every 4.2 million people. Uttar Pradesh has the least number of laboratories, 7, a laboratory for every 28 million people.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;Adulterated food and contaminated water affects the health of millions of Indians, often crippling and killing them. Unsafe food and water, containing harmful bacteria, parasites, viruses and chemical substances are responsible for nearly 200 diseases, across India and the world.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;So, on world health day, April 7, the slogan&amp;#8211;&amp;#8220;&lt;em&gt;From farm to plate, make food safe&lt;/em&gt;&amp;#8220;&amp;#8211; and the &lt;a href="http://www.who.int/campaigns/world-health-day/2015/campaign-toolkit-en.pdf"&gt;theme&lt;/a&gt;, food safety, appear particularly relevant to India.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;India is the worst in the world when it comes to deaths from diarrhoea with 11 out of every 100 children under the age of five who die, dying from diarrhoea. Among the BRICS (Brazil, Russia, India, China, South Africa) nations, South Africa is next with a diarrhoea death rate of 7%. China, the world&amp;#8217;s most populous country has a 4% diarrhoea death rate.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Diarrhoea &amp;#8211; Deaths among children under the 5 &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
</value>
    </content>
    <image>&lt;img href='FoodSafetygraph1.jpg' /&gt;</image>
    <width>567</width>
    <height>665</height>
    <content>
      <value>&lt;p&gt;Milk is India&amp;#8217;s most commonly adulterated food, as &lt;strong&gt;IndiaSpend&lt;/strong&gt; previously &lt;a href="http://www.indiaspend.com/cover-story/your-poisoned-food-our-unending-greed-31742"&gt;reported&lt;/a&gt;, with 68.4% of milk samples adulterated, as per the standards of the Food Safety Standards Authority of India.In 2013-14, of 72,200 &lt;a href="http://164.100.47.132/LssNew/psearch/QResult16.aspx?qref=6581"&gt;food samples&lt;/a&gt;, including milk/milk products, edible vegetable oils, spices, pulses, vegetables, regulatory officials found 13,571 samples adulterated and misbranded.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;IndiaSpend &lt;/strong&gt;also &lt;a href="http://www.indiaspend.com/cover-story/how-46-million-indians-are-being-slowly-poisoned-40865"&gt;reported&lt;/a&gt; that about 46 million people across 78,508 rural habitations in India use water contaminated with arsenic and fluoride&amp;#8211;both lead to serious health problems.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;Organised by the World Health Organisation (WHO), the &lt;a href="http://www.who.int/campaigns/world-health-day/2015/campaign-toolkit-en.pdf"&gt;aim&lt;/a&gt; of world health day is to spur governments to improve food safety through public-awareness campaigns and encourage consumers to ensure the food on their plate is safe by asking questions, checking labels and following hygiene tips.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;Diarrhoea, an intestinal tract infection that weaken the body, &lt;a href="http://164.100.47.132/Annexture_New/lsq16/3/au977.htm"&gt;killed&lt;/a&gt; 5,305 Indians between 2011 and September 2014, with 40 million cases registered.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;Another consequence of contaminated food and water is enteric fever or typhoid, a &lt;a href="http://www.who.int/topics/typhoid_fever/en/"&gt;bacterial disease&lt;/a&gt;, caused by &lt;em&gt;Salmonella typhi&lt;/em&gt;, transmitted by food or drink contaminated by the faeces or urine of infected people. Typhoid claimed 1,401 lives across India between 2011 and September 2014, with 5 million cases registered.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
</value>
    </content>
    <image>&lt;img href='FoodSafetygraph2.jpg' /&gt;</image>
    <width>558</width>
    <height>758</height>
    <image>&lt;img href='FoodSafetygraph3.jpg' /&gt;</image>
    <width>583</width>
    <height>775</height>
    <content>
      <value>&lt;p&gt;Globally, about 2 million people die each year from &lt;a href="http://www.who.int/campaigns/world-health-day/2015/campaign-toolkit-en.pdf"&gt;contaminated&lt;/a&gt; food or potable water, according to the WHO, and nearly 1.7 billion &lt;a href="http://www.who.int/mediacentre/factsheets/fs330/en/"&gt;cases&lt;/a&gt; of diarrhoeal disease are reported every year.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;Diarrhoea is also the second-largest killer of children globally, &lt;a href="http://data.unicef.org/child-health/diarrhoeal-disease"&gt;accounting&lt;/a&gt; for 9% of all deaths among children below the age of five. In 2013, an estimated 580,000 children&amp;#8211;or nearly 1,600 every day&amp;#8211;died of diarrhoeal infections.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;(&lt;strong&gt;Chaitanya Mallapur&lt;/strong&gt; is an analyst with IndiaSpend.)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Image Credit: &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/File:FDA_microbiologist_working_in_a_biosafety_laboratory_tests_for_high_risk_pathogens_in_food.jpg"&gt;Wikimedia&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;br&gt;&#13;
__________________________________________________________________________&lt;br&gt;&#13;
&amp;nbsp;&lt;br&gt;&#13;
&lt;em&gt;&amp;#8220;Liked this story? Indiaspend.com is a non-profit, and we depend on readers like you to drive our public-interest journalism efforts. &lt;a href="http://www.indiaspend.com/donate1" target="_blank"&gt;Donate&lt;/a&gt; Rs 500; Rs 1,000, Rs 2,000.&amp;#8221;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
</value>
    </content>
  </article>
</indiaspend>
