<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<indiaspend>
  <article>
    <title>India Slips A Notch In Global Press Freedom Score Ranking</title>
    <authorname>IndiaSpend Team</authorname>
    <date>May 3, 2014</date>
    <category>Politics</category>
    <content>
      <value>&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe src="http://www.openheatmap.com/embed.html?map=NonconnivanceOrnsteadsGoury" height="450" width="600"&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;International press freedom has declined to its lowest level in over a decade, according to the latest edition of the Freedom House&amp;#8217;s press freedom survey. Freedom House is a US-based independent organisation dedicated to the expansion of freedom around the world.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;div style="width:625px;margin-top:15px"&gt;&lt;div id="InRead"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;India was ranked 78th and the score declined by a point, to 39, to reflect increased interference in content by media owners in the run-up to the 2014 elections, which led to the dismissal of key editorial staff in several instances, the report said.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;The decline was driven in part by controls in several Middle Eastern states including Egypt, Libya, and Jordan and deterioration in the relatively open media environment of the United States.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;Of the 197 countries and territories assessed during 2013, a total of 63 (32%) were rated free, 68 (35%) were rated partly free and 66 (33%) were rated not free. The share of the world&amp;#8217;s population with media rated &amp;#8220;Free&amp;#8221; remains at just 14% or only one in seven people. Far larger shares live in &amp;#8220;Not Free&amp;#8221; (44%) or &amp;#8220;Partly Free&amp;#8221; (42%) media environments.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;While Netherlands, Norway and Sweden were ranked No 1 with completely free press, North Korea was ranked the last at 197.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
</value>
    </content>
  </article>
</indiaspend>
