<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<indiaspend>
  <article>
    <title>Guwahati, Srinagar at Highest Earthquake Risk</title>
    <authorname>Chaitanya Mallapur</authorname>
    <date>April 28, 2015</date>
    <category>Infrastructure</category>
    <image>&lt;img href='HighRisk_1.png' /&gt;</image>
    <width>627</width>
    <height>440</height>
    <content>
      <value>&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;Guwahati and Srinagar are the two Indian cities at highest risk of being devastated by an earthquake, with 36 other cities in areas prone to earthquakes, according to government data.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;div style="width:625px;margin-top:15px"&gt;&lt;div id="InRead"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Guwahati and Srinagar fall in what is called &amp;#8220;very severe intensity zone&amp;#8221;, or zone V, the highest-risk earthquake zone.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;Eight cities, including Delhi, fall in the &amp;#8220;severe intensity zone&amp;#8221; or zone IV, according to a seismic zoning map issued by the Bureau of Indian Standards and quoted in this National Disaster Management (NDM) &lt;a href="http://www.ndmindia.nic.in/EQProjects/ProgmDocmnt%20UEVRP.pdf"&gt;report&lt;/a&gt;. The other 30 cities fall in the &amp;#8220;moderate intensity zone&amp;#8221;, or zone III.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;This map shows India&amp;#8217;s 38 earthquake-prone cities:&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;</value>
    </content>
    <image>&lt;img href='HighRisk_2.png' /&gt;</image>
    <width>612</width>
    <height>590</height>
    <content>
      <value>&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;#8220;India has highly populous cities, including the national capital of New Delhi, located in zones of high seismic risk,&amp;#8221; said the report. &amp;#8220;Typically, the majority of the constructions in these cities are not earthquake resistant. Thus any earthquake striking in one of these cities would turn into a major disaster.&amp;#8221;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A reminder of India&amp;#8217;s vulnerability&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&#13;
The Nepal earthquake, which has now &lt;a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-asia-32475030"&gt;claimed&lt;/a&gt; more than 3,000 lives, and the NDM data are a reminder of India&amp;#8217;s vulnerability.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;IndiaSpend&lt;/strong&gt; recently &lt;a href="http://www.indiaspend.com/cover-story/38-indian-cities-in-high-risk-seismic-zones-17989"&gt;reported&lt;/a&gt; that nearly 60% of the sub-continental landmass is vulnerable to earthquakes.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;About &lt;a href="http://www.britannica.com/EBchecked/topic/238402/Gondwana"&gt;50 million years ago&lt;/a&gt;, India&amp;#8212;then an island that had previously broken off from a supercontinent called Gondwana, a name still used for what is now Chhattisgarh&amp;#8212;slammed into the Eurasian mainland, creating the Himalayas as it collided.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;All land on earth rides on &amp;#8220;plates&amp;#8221;, which glide on the mantle, a rocky inner layer. The Indian plate continues to grind into the Eurasian plate, and as it does, the Himalayas and north India are on shaky ground.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;India pushes northeast into Asia at roughly 5 cm every year, causing subterranean stresses that are released in the form of earthquakes every now and then.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Vulnerable zones are monitored, but prediction is impossible&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&#13;
An &lt;a href="http://www.isgn.gov.in/ISGN/HomePage.do?function=onPageLoad&amp;amp;target=aboutus"&gt;array of sensors in India&lt;/a&gt; and abroad monitor plate activity, but it is impossible to predict an earthquake, as many tweets and Whatsapp messages after the Nepal temblor appeared to indicate:&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
</value>
    </content>
    <image>&lt;img href='HighRisk_3.png' /&gt;</image>
    <width>535</width>
    <height>237</height>
    <content>
      <value>&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;What is available is data on areas of specific vulnerability.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;Gujarat and Uttar Pradesh appear to be the most vulnerable states, with six cities each in earthquake- prone zones. Both the states have one city each under zone IV and five cities marked under zone III.  Maharashtra is next with four cities in zone III.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The&lt;/strong&gt; Bureau of Indian Standards [IS-1893 &amp;#8211; part &amp;#8211; 1: 2002], &lt;a href="http://www.imd.gov.in/section/seismo/static/welcome.htm"&gt;based&lt;/a&gt; on scientific inputs from a number of agencies, including earthquake data supplied by Indian Meteorological Department (IMD), has grouped India into four seismic zones, II, III, IV and V.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="http://earthquake.usgs.gov/learn/topics/mercalli.php"&gt;Modified Mercalli (MM) intensity scale&lt;/a&gt;, which measures the impact of earthquakes on the surface of the earth, is broadly associated with India&amp;#8217;s earthquake zones, as follows:&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;</value>
    </content>
    <image>&lt;img href='HighRisk_4.png' /&gt;</image>
    <width>510</width>
    <height>190</height>
    <content>
      <value>&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;India has 42 digital &lt;a href="http://164.100.47.132/LssNew/psearch/QResult16.aspx?qref=11792"&gt;seismograph stations&lt;/a&gt; to measure earthquake magnitude and monitor earthquake activity, operated by the &lt;a href="http://india.gov.in/official-website-ministry-earth-sciences"&gt;Ministry of Earth Sciences&lt;/a&gt;.  As many as 78 new digital seismographs are likely to be installed during 2015-16.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;China, United States, Indonesia, Philippines and India were among the five countries world-wide most frequently hit by natural disasters over the last decade, according to this &lt;a href="http://cred.be/sites/default/files/ADSR_2013.pdf"&gt;report&lt;/a&gt; from the Center for Research on Epidemiology of Disasters.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;</value>
    </content>
    <image>&lt;img href='HighRisk_5.png' /&gt;</image>
    <width>521</width>
    <height>233</height>
    <content>
      <value>&#13;
</value>
    </content>
  </article>
</indiaspend>
