<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<indiaspend>
  <article>
    <title>Why India’s Nuclear Power Output Is Surging</title>
    <authorname>Amit Bhandari</authorname>
    <date>February 3, 2015</date>
    <category>Economy</category>
    <image>&lt;img href='IndiaNuclearPowercoverimage.jpg' /&gt;</image>
    <width>620</width>
    <height>396</height>
    <content>
      <value>&lt;div style="font-size: 11px;" align="left"&gt;Kudankulam nuclear power plant in Tamil Nadu&lt;/div&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;With Prime Minister Modi setting an ambitious goal of &lt;a href="http://indianexpress.com/article/india/india-others/pmo-sets-target-hike-n-power-capacity-three-fold-in-10-years/"&gt;tripling&lt;/a&gt; nuclear power over the next decade, an analysis by &lt;strong&gt;IndiaSpend&lt;/strong&gt; reveals that India&amp;#8217;s nuclear-power sector is in the best shape it has ever been to deliver that target.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;India is on course to double its nuclear power generation capacity to more than 10,000 mega watts (MW) over the next five years (see first table).&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;Generation of nuclear power in India has doubled over the past five years, as &lt;strong&gt;IndiaSpend&lt;/strong&gt; has earlier &lt;a href="http://www.indiaspend.com/special-reports/how-indias-nuclear-power-output-doubled-in-5-years-42326"&gt;reported&lt;/a&gt;. The new capacity under construction means nuclear power generation will double again over the next five years.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;The first of the new reactors under construction, the brand-new 1,000-MW power plant at &lt;a href="http://www.indiaspend.com/investigations/indias-nuclear-power-just-does-not-add-up"&gt;Kudankulam&lt;/a&gt;, Tamil Nadu, &lt;a href="http://www.npcil.nic.in/pdf/news_31dec2014_01.pdf"&gt;started&lt;/a&gt; commercial operations on December 31, 2014, while other projects are in the pipeline.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;</value>
    </content>
    <image>&lt;img href='IndiaNuclearPowergraph1.jpg' /&gt;</image>
    <width>655</width>
    <height>273</height>
    <content>
      <value>&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;The ongoing surge in nuclear power is a direct payoff of the India-US Civil Nuclear Agreement.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;The most publicised aspect of this deal is the four power plants that India hopes to build with foreign collaboration.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;Progress has been slow, leading some observers to &lt;a href="http://www.aninews.in/newsdetail2/story148426/india-achieved-nothing-from-indo-u-s-nuclear-deal-sitaram-yechury.html"&gt;write off&lt;/a&gt; the deal.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;The nuclear deal has already delivered clear, tangible gains for India, and will continue to do so in the coming years.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.indiaspend.com/special-reports/look-whos-minting-off-nuclear-power-hint-its-the-government-84733"&gt;Nuclear power&lt;/a&gt; plants account for 3.5% of India&amp;#8217;s current electricity generation, and its share in India&amp;#8217;s future electricity generation will be less than 10% even if the installed capacity is tripled. However, along with other sources of energy such as hydropower and solar-power, it will play a role in reducing India&amp;#8217;s reliance on coal for generating electricity.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;While progress on power reactors with foreign collaboration has been slow, India&amp;#8217;s indigenous reactor program is going along just fine.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;Four of the reactors are under construction: two each at Kakrapar and RAPP (Rajasthan) are indigenously designed 700 mw reactors. Work on another pair is expected to start in mid-2015 in Haryana, and six more are planned at three sites (see table below). These indigenously designed reactors appear set to be the workhorses of Indian nuclear program.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
</value>
    </content>
    <image>&lt;img href='IndiaNuclearPowergraph2.jpg' /&gt;</image>
    <width>649</width>
    <height>276</height>
    <content>
      <value>&lt;p&gt;India has been able to move ahead with these reactors because, unlike the past, fuel availability is no longer a problem.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;Before 2008, India&amp;#8217;s &lt;a href="http://www.indiaspend.com/viznomics/despite-all-nuclear-power-production-up-60-in-last-6-years"&gt;nuclear power&lt;/a&gt; reactors operated at 50% capacity because India did not produce sufficient uranium to run these reactors at full steam. As a non-signatory to the nuclear non-proliferation treaty, India was also locked out of the international nuclear marketplace and could not import fuel.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;All this changed after the Indo-US nuclear deal. India has since imported uranium from Kazakhstan, Russia and France and is exploring similar agreements with other suppliers, such as Australia.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;With more fuel available, capacity utilisation of nuclear power plants has improved from 50% in 2008-09 to more than 80% now (see table below).&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
</value>
    </content>
    <image>&lt;img href='IndiaNuclearPowergraph3.jpg' /&gt;</image>
    <width>647</width>
    <height>363</height>
    <content>
      <value>&lt;p&gt;Currently, 1,940 MW, about 40% of India&amp;#8217;s nuclear power capacity, operates under International Atomic Energy Agency (IAEA) safeguards and use &lt;a href="http://164.100.47.132/LssNew/psearch/QResult16.aspx?qref=6325"&gt;imported&lt;/a&gt; fuel.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="http://164.100.47.132/LssNew/psearch/QResult16.aspx?qref=7819"&gt;cost&lt;/a&gt; of imported fuel for running these reactors is Rs 330 crore per annum. The low cost of fuel is one of the reasons nuclear power is &lt;a href="http://164.100.47.132/LssNew/psearch/QResult16.aspx?qref=4083"&gt;cheaper&lt;/a&gt; than other fuels, such as coal or natural gas.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;Compared to power plants using fossil fuels, such as coal or gas, nuclear power has high initial costs. However, fuel cost is a minor expense during the plant&amp;#8217;s life, leading to lower lifetime costs for nuclear power compared to either coal or gas.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;Nuclear Power Corporation in India (NPCIL) supplies electricity at a lower cost per unit compared to any other energy utility in the public or private sector. Given India&amp;#8217;s status as a major importer of petroleum, natural gas and coal, this could be one way of keeping energy costs in check.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;_____________________________________________________________&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;#8220;Liked this story? Indiaspend.org is a non-profit, and we depend on readers like you to drive our public-interest journalism efforts.&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href="http://www.indiaspend.com/donate1" target="_blank"&gt;Donate&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;Rs 500; Rs 1,000, Rs 2,000.&amp;#8221;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
</value>
    </content>
  </article>
</indiaspend>
