<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<indiaspend>
  <article>
    <title>India’s Stuttering Internet Revolution</title>
    <authorname>Devanik Saha</authorname>
    <date>March 21, 2015</date>
    <category>Politics</category>
    <image>&lt;img href='InternetRevolutioncoverimage.jpg' /&gt;</image>
    <width>620</width>
    <height>450</height>
    <content>
      <value>&lt;p&gt;The year 2015 is supposed to be a seminal year for the Internet in India.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;div style="width:625px;margin-top:15px"&gt;&lt;div id="InRead"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is the year India is supposed to overtake the US&amp;#8212;it may already have, but there are no data, only estimates&amp;#8212;and become the world&amp;#8217;s second-largest user of the Net, with active internet users predicted to reach &lt;a href="http://www.iamai.in/rsh_pay.aspx?rid=4hjkHu7GsUU="&gt;269 million&lt;/a&gt; by June 2015. Claimed users are higher, with a figure of 302 million.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;#8217;s the rub: No more than 20.08 million actually use 3G, or third-generation mobile services (seven of eight Indian users access the Net on mobile phones), essential to viewing and sharing multimedia content.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;The average broadband speed in India is 2 Mbps (megabits per second). This puts India at a rank of 115 globally, lowest in the Asia-Pacific region, according to a &lt;a href="http://www.akamai.com/dl/content/q3-2014-state-of-the-internet-report.pdf"&gt;report&lt;/a&gt; by Akamai Technologies, a US technology company.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
</value>
    </content>
    <image>&lt;img href='InternetRevolutiongraph1.jpg' /&gt;</image>
    <width>494</width>
    <height>261</height>
    <image>&lt;img href='InternetRevolutiongraph2.jpg' /&gt;</image>
    <width>508</width>
    <height>249</height>
    <content>
      <value>&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;With the Internet now seen as having a &lt;a href="http://www.pewglobal.org/2015/03/19/internet-seen-as-positive-influence-on-education-but-negative-influence-on-morality-in-emerging-and-developing-nations/pg_15-03-11_internet-access_640px_web/"&gt;positive effect on education&lt;/a&gt; (but a negative impact on morality), in emerging nations, its spread would appear to be particularly important for India, but a new Pew research report also &lt;a href="http://www.pewglobal.org/2015/03/19/internet-seen-as-positive-influence-on-education-but-negative-influence-on-morality-in-emerging-and-developing-nations/pg_15-03-11_internet-access_640px_web/"&gt;classifies&lt;/a&gt; India as having low Internet usage.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;#8220;The so called explosive growth of the Internet (in India) is a misnomer,&amp;#8221; said Osama Manzar, founder-director of the Digital Empowerment Foundation (DEF), an advocacy group. &amp;#8220;Internet growth in India is still not exponential, it is going up step by step, not multiplying, as is being projected.&amp;#8221;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;More than 80% of Indian Net users are what Manzar called &amp;#8220;static users&amp;#8221;, or intermittently connected. Only between 2% to 5% of users are regular, which means their daily lives depend on the Net, which they use to contribute to the economy, he said.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;#8220;Wired broadband is quite insignificant in India,&amp;#8221; said Prasanto Roy, a commentator on information technology. &amp;#8220;It has not been an economic success. Of approximately &lt;a href="http://www.nextbigwhat.com/82-million-broadband-subscribers-india-297/"&gt;15 million&lt;/a&gt; wired broadband users, about 7-8 million are corporates and private-sector organisations.&amp;#8221;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;An ambitious government project to universalise broadband also struggles with access speeds.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;In October 2014, the Centre started the &lt;a href="http://www.bbnl.nic.in/content/page/national-optical-fibre-networknofn.php"&gt;National Optical Fiber Network&lt;/a&gt;, to bring broadband to 250,000 &lt;em&gt;gram panchayats&lt;/em&gt; (village councils). A state-owned company, Bharat Broadband Network Limited, was created to implement the project.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;Connectivity is patchy&amp;#8212;at best. Only 67% of panchayats, in the pilot phase, were actually connected to the national fibre network (20.5% had no connection at all), but no more than 45.5% of panchayats had access to services, said a December 2014 DEF &lt;a href="http://defindia.org/files/2015/01/Internet-Access.pdf"&gt;study&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;Rajnish (he uses only one name), a technology entrepreneur, said there were two ways to improve India&amp;#8217;s broadband situation: Allow private operators to use the fixed subscriber lines of state-run telecommunications companies MTNL &amp;amp; BSNL to provide internet access; and cut taxes to private service providers.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;#8220;But overall, I believe, investing in fixed-line broadband internet doesn&amp;#8217;t make sense,&amp;#8221; said Rajnish.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;India also struggles with broadband on mobile internet services.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;With an average speed of 1.7 Mbps, India ranks below Thailand, China, Hong Kong and Singapore. Globally, India ranks better than Brazil but falls behind other major economies.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;#8220;About 60 million mobile users are intermittent 2G users, who mainly use Facebook and WhatsApp applications once or twice a day,&amp;#8221; said Roy.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
</value>
    </content>
    <image>&lt;img href='InternetRevolutiongraph3.jpg' /&gt;</image>
    <width>509</width>
    <height>265</height>
    <image>&lt;img href='InternetRevolutiongraph4.jpg' /&gt;</image>
    <width>511</width>
    <height>268</height>
    <content>
      <value>&lt;p&gt;There&amp;#8217;s no dearth of demand for broadband. India is the &lt;a href="http://www.livemint.com/Consumer/jssXBoP3nMkZOOGbXOCdeL/India-fastest-growing-smartphone-mkt-in-Asia-Pacific-IDC.html"&gt;fastest&lt;/a&gt;-growing smartphone market in the Asia-Pacific region, with smartphone sales estimated at &lt;a href="http://articles.economictimes.indiatimes.com/2014-11-26/news/56490182_1_smartphone-sales-feature-phones-micromax"&gt;53 million&lt;/a&gt; in 2014, compared to personal computer sales of &lt;a href="http://www.business-standard.com/article/technology/pc-sales-down-16-5-in-2014-idc-115030400519_1.html"&gt;9.6 million&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;Speeds may only increase if 4G, or fourth-generation services, become widespread. Reliance Jio is &lt;a href="http://www.business-standard.com/article/companies/reliance-jio-to-roll-out-services-in-800-cities-114121700005_1.html"&gt;expected&lt;/a&gt; to launch its 4G LTE services across 800 cities in May/June 2015. But it had acquired spectrum, or telecommunication airwaves, almost four years ago and was waiting for clarity in telecom policy and better technology.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;In response to Reliance Jio, and with a possible objective to gain an early edge, Airtel, which offers some 4G services, has also &lt;a href="http://www.thehindubusinessline.com/features/smartbuy/tech-news/airtel-takes-4g-battle-to-reliance-jios-backyard/article6808883.ece"&gt;speeded up&lt;/a&gt; up its roll-out plans.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;(&lt;strong&gt;Devanik Saha&lt;/strong&gt; is Data Editor at &lt;a href="http://www.thepoliticalindian.com/"&gt;The Political Indian&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Image Credit: &lt;a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/mikecogh/1051563590/sizes/o/"&gt;Flickr/MikeCogH&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;br&gt;&#13;
__________________________________________________________________________&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;#8220;Liked this story? Indiaspend.com is a non-profit, and we depend on readers like you to drive our public-interest journalism efforts. &lt;a href="http://www.indiaspend.com/donate1" target="_blank"&gt;Donate&lt;/a&gt; Rs 500; Rs 1,000, Rs 2,000.&amp;#8221;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
</value>
    </content>
  </article>
</indiaspend>
