<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<indiaspend>
  <article>
    <title>How Modi’s Govt Is Scrapping A Scheme Gujarat Benefited Most From</title>
    <authorname>Prachi Salve</authorname>
    <date>June 6, 2014</date>
    <category>Economy</category>
    <image>&lt;img href='jnnurm_pic1.jpg' /&gt;</image>
    <width>600</width>
    <height>320</height>
    <content>
      <value>&lt;p&gt;India&amp;#8217;s urban Development Minister Venkaiah Naidu announced &lt;a href=\"http://www.livemint.com/Politics/HQbQUgombjdYbOiPGD0ikN/Govt-to-bring-new-scheme-to-replace-JNNURM.html\"&gt;recently&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;the new BJP-led Government would be scrapping the Jawaharlal Nehru National Urban Renewal Mission (JNNURM), an urban infrastructure fund and brainchild of the previous government. He claimed it was too centralised and did not allow states much space for policy maneuvering.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;The Government now plans to launcha new mission which will focuson &amp;#8220;spatial planning, liquid and solid waste management and public transport, among other things.&amp;#8221;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;The JNNURM might have faced glitches but it provided a useful proxy, including to folks like us, to gauge urban infrastructure investment and build across cities like India.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;We have two key findings to report from the latest available numbers. First, the state of Gujarat led by now Prime Minister and former Chief Minister Narendra Modi for more than a decade until May 2014 was actually one of the largest absorbers of JNNURM funds and used it effectively to build infrastructure in its cities. Second, the city of Bangalore now has the maximum number of completed projects, overtaking Ahmedabad and Surat, which led the league tables until last year.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;So, what has been the story of JNNURM since itslaunchin 2005-06?&amp;nbsp; The aim of JNNURM was to improve cities across the country by developing physical infrastructure and local governance. Though the programme was to end in 2012, it was to be extended by two years to 2014 if the previous Congress-led UPA Government were to be elected.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;So what has been the story of JNNURM since its launch in 2005-06?&amp;nbsp; JNNURM&amp;#8217;s objective was to improve cities across the country by developing physical infrastructure and local governance. Though the programme was to end in 2012, it was to be extended by two years to 2014.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;The mission was initially divided into two sub-missions:&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;br&gt;&#13;
1.&amp;nbsp;Urban Infrastructure and Governance (UIG); and&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;br&gt;&#13;
2. &amp;nbsp;Basic Services to the Urban Poor (BSUP)&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;Two other components were added later to accommodate more cities and towns:&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;1.&amp;nbsp;Urban Infrastructure Development for Small and Medium Towns Scheme (UIDSSMT); and&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;2.&amp;nbsp;Integrated Housing and Slum Development Programme (IHSDP).&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;A &lt;a href=\"http://saiindia.gov.in/english/home/Our_Products/Audit_Report/Government_Wise/union_audit/recent_reports/union_performance/2012_2013/Commercial/Report_15/Report_15.html\"&gt;report&lt;/a&gt;by the Government&amp;#8217;s auditor, Comptroller &amp;amp; Auditor General (CAG), says the mission was allocated Rs66,084 crore by the Planning Commission between 2005-06 and 2011-12. &amp;nbsp;As against this, Rs45,066 crore was the actual budgetary allocation during the same period. &amp;nbsp;And nearly 90% of the budgetary allocation (Rs 40,584 crore) was released for the various programmes of the mission.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;So which states and cities have completed the maximum number of projects?&lt;/p&gt;</value>
    </content>
    <image>&lt;img href='jnnurm_pic2.jpg' /&gt;</image>
    <width>629</width>
    <height>280</height>
    <content>
      <value>&lt;p&gt;Tamil Nadu has completed the maximum number of projects (102) out of the 136 sanctioned projects followed by AP with 70 out of the 84 projects under UIDDSMT.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;</value>
    </content>
    <image>&lt;img href='jnnurm_pic3.jpg' /&gt;</image>
    <width>661</width>
    <height>384</height>
    <content>
      <value>&lt;p&gt;Bangalore completed the highest number of the projects (23) out of 38 sanctioned projects followed by Ahmedabad and Surat with 22 and 19, respectively. Note that Bangalore, Kolkata and Chennai are larger cities and Ahmedabad and Surat have clearly been more effective in sourcing and utilising the funds. Ahmedabad has completed only 4 projects since 2012 when we had reported &lt;a href=\"http://www.indiaspend.com/investigations/why-gujarats-urban-infrastructure-build-is-as-real-as-it-appears\"&gt;earlier&lt;/a&gt; 19 completed projects.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Financial Management&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;The table below shows the funds released under additional central assistance (ACA) from 2005-06 to2011-12 for UIG and UIDSSMT.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;</value>
    </content>
    <image>&lt;img href='jnnurm_pic4.png' /&gt;</image>
    <width>569</width>
    <height>268</height>
    <content>
      <value>&lt;p&gt;A total of 79% (i.e. Rs 18,543.66 crore) was released under the UIG component out of the total budgetary allocation of Rs 23,469 crore. And 83.5% (i.e. Rs 7,342.96 crore) were released under the UIDSSSMT component of the total budgetary allocation of Rs 8,792.2 crore.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;Under the JNNURM the funding pattern, the centre pays 35%, the state pays 15% and the urban local body or the municipal corporation pays 50% of the project funding.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;According to the &lt;a href=\"http://saiindia.gov.in/english/home/Our_Products/Audit_Report/Government_Wise/union_audit/recent_reports/union_performance/2012_2013/Commercial/Report_15/Report_15.html\"&gt;CAG&lt;/a&gt; report, funds released were dependent on the condition that reforms would be implemented by urban local bodies (ULBs). This was not done by most states and hence the delay in release of funds to the states. Another reason for the late release of funds was the seeming delays in approval process of the central Government and the inability of the state Governments to complete the requisite formalities.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;So, how many projects were sanctioned and how many were completed under JNNURM?&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
</value>
    </content>
    <image>&lt;img href='jnnurm_pic5.png' /&gt;</image>
    <width>819</width>
    <height>297</height>
  </article>
</indiaspend>
