<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<indiaspend>
  <article>
    <title>God’s Own Country, Kerala, Has Worst Drinking Water Quality In India</title>
    <authorname>IndiaSpend Team</authorname>
    <date>March 27, 2014 </date>
    <category>States</category>
    <image>&lt;img href='keralawater.png' /&gt;</image>
    <width>658</width>
    <height>562</height>
    <content>
      <value>&lt;p&gt;Yes, its true. Kerala has access to the lowest quality of drinking water in rural areas across the states of India, according to a report published by the National Sample Survey Organisation. The &lt;a href=\"http://mospi.nic.in/Mospi_New/upload/kye_indi_of_water_Sanitation69rou_24dec13.pdf\" target=\"_blank\"&gt;report&lt;/a&gt; says that only 29.5% of rural households in Kerala had access to safe drinking water, a figure which is &lt;a href=\"http://164.100.47.132/LssNew/psearch/QResult15.aspx?qref=149851\" target=\"_blank\"&gt;grossly &lt;/a&gt;below the all-India average of 88.5%.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;Kerala also had the highest chemical/bacterial contaminated drinking water among 28 tested states in the country, as per the Union Ministry of Drinking Water and Sanitation from the State&amp;#8217;s Economic Review for 2011-2012, &lt;a href=\"http://www.thehindu.com/news/national/kerala/kerala-has-most-contaminated-drinking-water/article4511832.ece\" target=\"_blank\"&gt;reported &lt;/a&gt;The Hindu.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;The states that had the highest proportion of access to safe drinking water was Punjab, Himachal Pradesh, Bihar.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;While this may come across as a bit of shock, we had &lt;a href=\"http://www.indiaspend.com/states/extreme-state-kerala-42301\" target=\"_blank\"&gt;reported &lt;/a&gt;earlier that Kerala is a sharp study of contrasts. On one hand, it has the highest literacy in the country and has seen a sharp decline in poverty rates from nearly 34% in 1993-94 to 12% in 2009-10 in both rural and urban areas. It also has another side. The state has seen a sharp increase in suicide rates and crimes. Read the rest here.&lt;/p&gt;</value>
    </content>
  </article>
</indiaspend>
