<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<indiaspend>
  <article>
    <title>Kerala’s New Gambit: Pay Interest On Agri Loans</title>
    <authorname>IndiaSpend Team</authorname>
    <date>March 23, 2015</date>
    <category>Politics</category>
    <image>&lt;img href='KeralaNewGambitcoverimage.jpg' /&gt;</image>
    <width>620</width>
    <height>413</height>
    <content>
      <value>&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;The Kerala government is planning a unique experiment to tackle the agrarian crisis. Presenting the &lt;a href="http://www.finance.kerala.gov.in/index.php?option=com_content&amp;amp;view=article&amp;amp;id=529:kerala-budget-2015-16&amp;amp;catid=18:state-budget"&gt;budget&lt;/a&gt; for the year 2015-16, Finance Minister K. M. Mani announced that the government will pay the entire interest payable by farmers on every loan where the farmer repays the principal on time.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;div style="width:625px;margin-top:15px"&gt;&lt;div id="InRead"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;The minister also set aside Rs 125 crore next year for the scheme. &amp;#8220;I am confident that this will increase the inflow of agricultural credit into the state by an additional Rs 2,000 crore,&amp;#8221; the minister said in his budget speech.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;A &lt;a href="http://mospi.nic.in/Mospi_New/upload/KI_70_33_19dec14.pdf"&gt;report&lt;/a&gt; by the National Sample Survey Organisation (NSSO) titled &lt;em&gt;Key Indicators of Situation of Agricultural Households in India&lt;/em&gt; released in December 2014 said that Kerala was the state with the highest average outstanding loan per agricultural household.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
</value>
    </content>
    <image>&lt;img href='KeralaNewGambitgraph1.jpg' /&gt;</image>
    <width>509</width>
    <height>260</height>
    <content>
      <value>&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;Kerala had only 27% rural households classified as agricultural households as against the national average of 57.8%. Out of a total of 5,137,700 rural households in Kerala, only 1,404,300 households were agricultural households. (This means only 5.5 million people are dependent on agriculture in Kerala.)&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
</value>
    </content>
    <image>&lt;img href='KeralaNewGambitgraph2.jpg' /&gt;</image>
    <width>534</width>
    <height>239</height>
    <content>
      <value>&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;Kerala was followed by Tamil Nadu with 34.7% of rural households classified as agricultural, ahead of former Andhra Pradesh (41.5%), West Bengal (45%) and Punjab (51.1%). The percentage for India as a whole is 57.8%.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;How much agriculture credit is outstanding in Kerala? Here&amp;#8217;s a look at the numbers from Kerala State Co-operative Agricultural and Rural Development Bank (KSCARD Bank):&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
</value>
    </content>
    <image>&lt;img href='KeralaNewGambitgraph3.jpg' /&gt;</image>
    <width>528</width>
    <height>256</height>
    <content>
      <value>&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, a &lt;a href="http://www.rbi.org.in/scripts/PublicationReportDetails.aspx?ID=697"&gt;study&lt;/a&gt; by Reserve Bank of India in 2013 found that the gross level of credit of central credit bodies in Kerala averaged Rs 34,401 crore ($5.5 billion) for the years 2009-10 to 2011-12. Out of this, only Rs 6,926 crore ($1.12 billion) was for agriculture loans.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;Kerala, which has a population of 33 million, is ahead on all social indicators like education, health and sex ratio.&amp;nbsp; While the literary rate is 90.86% as against the national rate of 73%, sex ratio (females per 1,000 males)&amp;nbsp; is 1,058 as against the national average of 943.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;Infant mortality rate, an &lt;a href="http://censusindia.gov.in/vital_statistics/SRS_Bulletins/SRS%20Bulletin%20-Sepetember%202014.pdf"&gt;estimate&lt;/a&gt; of infant deaths for every 1,000 live births, is only 12 in Kerala as against the national average of 40.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;Maternal mortality ratio, the number of women aged 15-49 dying due to maternal causes per 100,000 live births, is 61 in Kerala as against the national average of 167.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;The question is &amp;#8211; will the experiment of the Congress-led United Democratic Front (UDF) work in Kerala? And can that be replicated across the country instead of the &lt;a href="http://saiindia.gov.in/english/home/our_products/audit_report/Government_Wise/union_audit/recent_reports/union_performance/2013/Civil/Report_3/Report_3.html"&gt;controversy-ridden&lt;/a&gt; Rs 520,000 crore ($8.39 billion) agricultural debt-waiver scheme of the first UPA government?&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Image credit: &lt;a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/pondspider/3686006791/sizes/o/"&gt;Flickr/Anne Roberts&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;br&gt;&#13;
__________________________________________________________________________&lt;br&gt;&#13;
&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;#8220;Liked this story? Indiaspend.com is a non-profit, and we depend on readers like you to drive our public-interest journalism efforts. &lt;a href="http://www.indiaspend.com/donate1" target="_blank"&gt;Donate&lt;/a&gt; Rs 500; Rs 1,000, Rs 2,000.&amp;#8221;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
</value>
    </content>
  </article>
</indiaspend>
