<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<indiaspend>
  <article>
    <title>Why Indians Are Losing Out On Libraries</title>
    <authorname>Subadra Ramakrishnan</authorname>
    <date>January 10, 2015</date>
    <category>Politics</category>
    <image>&lt;img href='Librariescoverimage.jpg' /&gt;</image>
    <width>620</width>
    <height>366</height>
    <content>
      <value>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;#8220;The only thing that you absolutely have to know is the location of the library.&amp;#8221;&amp;nbsp;&amp;#8213;&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href="http://www.goodreads.com/author/show/9810.Albert_Einstein"&gt;Albert Einstein&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;They have been called &amp;#8220;raucous clubhouses for free speech&amp;#8221;. They have been called &amp;#8220;delivery rooms for the birth of ideas&amp;#8221;. Without them, societies have been warned, that they have &amp;#8220;no past and no future&amp;#8221;. With them, societies have been assured, there is no better protection against tyranny, xenophobia and ignorance.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;With such widespread and deep intellectual backing across the world, India was no stranger to the great benefits of public libraries.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;Sayyaji Rao Gaekwad III, the Maharaja of Baroda, who &lt;a href="http://www.nmlindia.nic.in/pages/display/24"&gt;kick-started&lt;/a&gt; the public-library system in 1910, wanted his people to be &amp;#8220;pupils in the people&amp;#8217;s university&amp;#8221;. The kingdom of Kolhapur, in what is now Maharashtra, passed India&amp;#8217;s first Public Library Act in 1945. Since then, 19 Indian states&amp;#8211;the latest being Arunachal Pradesh in 2009&amp;#8211;have passed laws enabling the &lt;a href="http://rrrlf.nic.in/lib_legislation.asp"&gt;establishment&lt;/a&gt; of libraries open to the public.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;Yet, India with its 1.2 billion people and after seven decades of independence, does not know how many public libraries it has.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;Using a conservative estimate of 35,000 libraries, based on calculations by Raja Rammohun Roy Library Foundation (RRRLF), a trust which funds public libraries and comes under the aegis of the Ministry of Culture, there is only one library per 36,000 people.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;Compare that with &lt;a href="https://oclc.org/global-library-statistics.en.html"&gt;China&lt;/a&gt; with a 2013 population of 1.36 billion and 51,311 libraries i.e. one public library per roughly 26,000 people. The &lt;a href="http://www.ala.org/tools/libfactsheets/alalibraryfactsheet01"&gt;United States&lt;/a&gt; with a population of 315 million and 16,500 public libraries has one library for every 19,000 people.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;An effort to correct the anomaly was the launch of National Mission on Libraries (NML) in February 2014 by President Pranab Mukherjee. Acknowledging the critical role of libraries&amp;#8211;and apparently paraphrasing the Maharaja of Baroda&amp;#8211;&lt;a href="http://www.pib.nic.in/newsite/erelease.aspx?relid=102963"&gt;Mukherjee said&lt;/a&gt;: &amp;#8220;A public library is often called the &amp;#8220;people&amp;#8217;s university&amp;#8221; because it is available to all sections of the society regardless of age, gender, or skill levels.&amp;#8221;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;The Government of India has allocated Rs 400 crore for the National Mission on Libraries over the &lt;a href="http://rrrlf.nic.in/nml_launch.asp"&gt;next three years&lt;/a&gt;, including the creation of a national virtual library, model libraries and staff training.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;But India&amp;#8217;s largest, most-populous states don&amp;#8217;t really care.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;As the graph below indicates, large states such as Bihar, Madhya Pradesh, Orissa and Jharkhand have not bothered to even apply for the money available. Only 2% of the total 12,000+ libraries that received assistance were in Uttar Pradesh, the most populous state in the country.&lt;/p&gt;</value>
    </content>
    <image>&lt;img href='Librariesgraph1.jpg' /&gt;</image>
    <width>691</width>
    <height>730</height>
    <content>
      <value>&lt;p&gt;The Foundation helps states customise libraries, but no more than 12,000 libraries are formally registered and, according to this&lt;a href="http://rrrlf.nic.in/annual_report_12-13.asp"&gt; 2012-2013 report&lt;/a&gt;, the national average for funds used stood at 27%. Delhi used all the funds available, followed by Chandigarh at 81%. Many states hovered around the 40% mark, but states like Bihar, Punjab, Madhya Pradesh, and Haryana did not use any of the funds available.&lt;br&gt;</value>
    </content>
    <image>&lt;img href='Librariesgraph2.jpg' /&gt;</image>
    <width>676</width>
    <height>740</height>
    <content>
      <value>&lt;p&gt;Not surprisingly, states without proper public-library systems have low literacy rates. States with higher literacy rates consistently utilised a bigger portion of state funds earmarked for library improvement programs as compared to states with lower literacy.&lt;/p&gt;</value>
    </content>
    <image>&lt;img href='Librariesgraph3.jpg' /&gt;</image>
    <width>661</width>
    <height>728</height>
    <content>
      <value>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;When the system &lt;em&gt;does&lt;/em&gt; work&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;There are some common traits among states that have a vibrant public-library system, such as Kerala, West Bengal, Maharashtra, Gujarat to name a few.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;One, they have fully functional websites, with details and membership forms, online catalogs, details of manuscripts and journalsand other essential information.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;Two, most of them have adopted the library legislation, which gives them benchmarks to monitor and improve on.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;Three, they regularly tap into RRRLF resources to scale up infrastructure, buy more books, digitise existing books and train staff. The table below gives you a snapshot of states that are serious about public libraries:&lt;/p&gt;</value>
    </content>
    <image>&lt;img href='Librariestable1.jpg' /&gt;</image>
    <width>670</width>
    <height>569</height>
    <content>
      <value>&lt;p&gt;The National Mission on Libraries makes sense, but the basic problem remains: How will it help libraries if the RRRLF&amp;#8211;the implementing agency&amp;#8211;does not know that they exist, apart from the 12,000 officially registered?&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;A central online repository of all public libraries in the country might help.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;There are many benefits to a vastly improved public-library system across India, with &lt;a href="http://firstmonday.org/ojs/index.php/fm/article/view/2588/2237"&gt;suggestions&lt;/a&gt; to link them to, among others, literacy programmes and community services.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;As this paper &lt;a href="http://firstmonday.org/ojs/index.php/fm/article/view/2588/2237"&gt;said&lt;/a&gt;: &amp;#8220;India is in a position to redefine what a public library means, especially with regard to the delivery of community information services and the preservation of local cultural traditions. These are exciting and important times, as a vast number of India&amp;#8217;s citizens can serve to benefit from improved public library services&amp;#8230;&amp;#8230;(We need) to continue building this new vision, and&amp;#8230;(engage in) sustained and creative action. Millions are waiting.&amp;#8221;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;(&lt;em&gt;Subadra Ramakrishnan&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;em&gt; is a freelance writer and licensed pilot who lives in New Delhi. You can reach her at: &lt;/em&gt;&lt;a href="mailto:bsubadra@gmail.com"&gt;&lt;em&gt;bsubadra@gmail.com&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;Image Credit: &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/File:India_Education.jpg"&gt;Wikimedia&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;br&gt;&#13;
_____________________________________________________________&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;#8220;Liked this story? Indiaspend.org is a non-profit, and we depend on readers like you to drive our public-interest journalism efforts. &lt;a href="http://www.indiaspend.com/donate1"&gt;Donate&lt;/a&gt; Rs 500; Rs 1,000, Rs 2,000.&amp;#8221;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
</value>
    </content>
  </article>
</indiaspend>
