<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<indiaspend>
  <article>
    <title>Maharashtra CM Faces 22 Riot Cases, Crime Accused Pack Assembly</title>
    <authorname>Prachi Salve</authorname>
    <date>October 27, 2014</date>
    <category>Politics</category>
    <image>&lt;img href='coverimage.jpg' /&gt;</image>
    <width>641</width>
    <height>426</height>
    <content>
      <value>&lt;em&gt;(Maharashtra BJP president and Chief Minister Devendra Fadnavis with other party leaders)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;*Devendra Fadnavis, the Bharatiya Janata Party (BJP) chief minister, has 22 charges of rioting registered against him.&lt;br&gt;&#13;
&amp;nbsp;&lt;br&gt;&#13;
* Jitendra Ahwad&amp;#8212;the only member of the legislative assembly (MLA) with a doctorate&amp;#8212;of the Nationalist Congress Party (NCP) has 15 criminal cases against him, including kidnapping.&lt;br&gt;&#13;
&amp;nbsp;&lt;br&gt;&#13;
* Of 20 women MLAs, seven face criminal charges; five face serious charges including crime against women.&lt;br&gt;&#13;
&amp;nbsp;&lt;br&gt;&#13;
* 50 MLAs, now supposed to work with government officers and uphold the law, are charged with assault against public servants.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;The Maharashtra assembly elections are over, and the BJP has emerged the single largest party, riding a wave of public desire for change and progress.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;Far from changing, the one thing set to worsen is the criminal record of the state&amp;#8217;s new MLAs.&lt;br&gt;&#13;
&amp;nbsp;&lt;br&gt;&#13;
A &lt;a href=\"http://adrindia.org/research-and-report/election-watch/state-assemblies/maharashtra/2014/analysis-criminal-financial-and\"&gt;report&lt;/a&gt; by New Delhi-based Association for Democratic Reforms (ADR) mentioned that out of 2,336 candidates of various parties, 798 had criminal cases against them. An &lt;strong&gt;IndiaSpend&lt;/strong&gt; analysis shows that out of the 288-member assembly, 165 members have criminal cases against them, which is 57%. The results of this election have thrown up the highest percentage of MLAs with declared criminal charges, as against 52% in 2009 and 46% in 2004.&lt;br&gt;</value>
    </content>
    <image>&lt;img href='maharashtracmtable1.jpg' /&gt;</image>
    <width>639</width>
    <height>174</height>
    <content>
      <value>&lt;p&gt;Of 165 MLAs facing criminal charges, nearly 70% (115 MLAs) have serious criminal charges against them. Serious criminal charges include murder and attempt to murder, kidnapping, forgery and rioting.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;Over the last few elections there has been an increase in the number of MLAs with serious charges, from 54 MLAs in 2004 to 115 in 2014.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;Let us now look at the party-wise position:&lt;/p&gt;</value>
    </content>
    <image>&lt;img href='maharashtracmgraph1.jpg' /&gt;</image>
    <width>644</width>
    <height>429</height>
    <content>
      <value>&lt;p&gt;BJP, which is the largest party with 122 seats, also has the highest number of MLAs with criminal charges at 74, which is 60% of its MLAs. It also has the highest number of MLAs facing serious criminal charges at 53 i.e. 43%. Second on the list is the Shiv Sena with 48 of its 63 MLAs (76%) facing criminal charges. The party also stands second with the number of MLAs facing serious criminal charges at 36 (57%).&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;Here is a look at the region-wise story:&lt;/p&gt;</value>
    </content>
    <image>&lt;img href='maharashtracmgraph2.jpg' /&gt;</image>
    <width>690</width>
    <height>380</height>
    <content>
      <value>&lt;p&gt;Vidharbha has the highest number of MLAs (58%) facing criminal charges. Vidarbha is followed by the Konkan region, with 57% MLAs facing criminal charges. Khandesh has the highest number of MLAs with serious criminal cases against them (48%).&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;So, what are the kinds of serious crimes registered against MLAs in Maharashtra?&lt;/p&gt;</value>
    </content>
    <image>&lt;img href='maharashtracmgraph3.jpg' /&gt;</image>
    <width>650</width>
    <height>434</height>
    <content>
      <value>&lt;p&gt;So, rioting is the most serious charge against MLAs, with cases against 81 representatives, followed by hurt/assault on public servant (50) and cheating (31).&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;Now, here are some interesting facts:&lt;br&gt;&#13;
&amp;nbsp;&lt;br&gt;&#13;
* In cheating cases, one noteworthy figure is Praniti Shinde, daughter of former chief minister and union home minister Sushil Kumar Shinde.&lt;br&gt;&#13;
&amp;nbsp;&lt;br&gt;&#13;
* Hitendra Thakur of the Bahujan Vikas Aghadi not only faces eight cases, including bribery and rioting, but has declared assets of Rs 100 crore.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;br&gt;&#13;
(This is an updated version of an earlier story)&lt;br&gt;&#13;
&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;Visualisation: Chaitanya Mallapur&lt;br&gt;&#13;
&amp;nbsp;&lt;br&gt;&#13;
Data Inputs: Mrinmoyee Chatterjee&lt;br&gt;&#13;
&amp;nbsp;&lt;br&gt;&#13;
Photo Credit: BJP (Maharashtra)&lt;/p&gt;</value>
    </content>
  </article>
</indiaspend>
