<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<indiaspend>
  <article>
    <title>India Has 381 Medical Colleges, Needs 240 More</title>
    <authorname>IndiaSpend Team</authorname>
    <date>July 1, 2014</date>
    <category>Education</category>
    <image>&lt;img href='MedicalCollegescoverimage.jpg' /&gt;</image>
    <width>512</width>
    <height>341</height>
    <content>
      <value>&lt;p&gt;India&amp;#8217;s Health Minister Dr Harsh Vardhan (an ENT surgeon himself) recently &lt;a href="http://www.pib.nic.in/newsite/erelease.aspx?relid=105959"&gt;asked doctors&lt;/a&gt; to introspect and correct the `wrong&amp;#8217; public perception about the profession.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;He also highlighted the need for more doctors across the country. What is the gap between doctors available and what is desired? On &lt;b&gt;Doctor&amp;#8217;s Day&lt;/b&gt; (July 1), here are some quick facts:&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;* The &lt;a href="http://www.planningcommission.gov.in/plans/planrel/12thplan/pdf/12fyp_vol3.pdf"&gt;12th Plan document&lt;/a&gt; released by the Planning Commission says &amp;nbsp;922,177 physicians are enrolled at the end of 2011-12 and 691,633 are available, giving a density (per lakh population) of 57.&amp;nbsp; According to &lt;a href="http://www.who.int/gho/countries/ind.pdf?ua=1"&gt;World Health Organisation&lt;/a&gt;, India had 7 physicians per 10,000 population as against Brazil, which has 18.9 physicians per 10,000 population and the United States, which has 24 physicians for 10,000 population.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;* Expected availability is 848,616 doctors by 2017 to give a doctor density of 65.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;* But 240 medical colleges will be needed if India is to meet the desired doctor density of 85.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;* According to &lt;a href="http://www.mciindia.org/InformationDesk/ForStudents/ListofCollegesTeachingMBBS.aspx"&gt;Medical Council of India&lt;/a&gt;, India currently has 381 medical colleges and 50,078 seats at the graduate level. While Brazil has over 180 medical colleges, the United States has over 140 medical colleges.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
</value>
    </content>
    <image>&lt;img href='MedicalCollegesgraph1.jpg' /&gt;</image>
    <width>634</width>
    <height>203</height>
    <content>
      <value>&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Health Indicators&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;* Infant mortality rate (IMR) has dropped to 44 in 2011 from 57 in 2006.&lt;br&gt;&#13;
* Maternal mortality ratio (MMR) has declined to 212 per 100,000 live births from 254 in 2004-06.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Targets&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;br&gt;&#13;
&lt;/b&gt;* Reduce IMR to 25 by the end of the 12th Plan (2017)&lt;br&gt;&#13;
* Bring down MMR to 100 by the end of the 12th Plan (2017)&lt;br&gt;&#13;
* Increase public health spending to 1.87% of GDP by the end of the Twelfth Plan; cost-free access to essential medicines in public facilities.&lt;br&gt;&#13;
* Reduce out-of-pocket spending as a proportion of private spending on health.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
</value>
    </content>
  </article>
</indiaspend>
