<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<indiaspend>
  <article>
    <title>Can A 6-Party Combo Challenge Modi’s Charisma?</title>
    <authorname>IndiaSpend Team</authorname>
    <date>April 1, 2015</date>
    <category>Politics</category>
    <image>&lt;img href='ModiCharismacoverimage.jpg' /&gt;</image>
    <width>620</width>
    <height>440</height>
    <content>
      <value>&lt;p&gt;The followers of former socialist leaders Ram Manohar Lohia and Jayaprakash Narayan, currently running their own parties, are planning a &lt;a href="http://timesofindia.indiatimes.com/india/No-hiccups-in-Janata-Parivar-merger-KC-Tyagi/articleshow/46769486.cms"&gt;grand union &lt;/a&gt;to form a new party, whose name will be either &lt;strong&gt;Samajwadi Janata Dal&lt;/strong&gt; or &lt;strong&gt;Samajwadi Janata Party.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;div style="width:625px;margin-top:15px"&gt;&lt;div id="InRead"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;The aim:&lt;strong&gt; &amp;nbsp;&lt;/strong&gt;take on the might of Narendra Modi-Amit Shah led Bharatiya Janata Party (BJP).&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;The six parties in the process of uniting are:&lt;br&gt;&#13;
1) Bihar Chief Minister Nitish Kumar-led Janata Dal (United) JD (U)&lt;br&gt;&#13;
2) Lalu Prasad&amp;#8217;s Rashtriya Janata Dal (RJD)&lt;br&gt;&#13;
3) Samajwadi Party (SP)&lt;br&gt;&#13;
4) Om Prakash Chautala&amp;#8217;s Indian National Lok Dal (INLD)&lt;br&gt;&#13;
5) Janata Dal (Secular) led by former Prime Minister HD Deve Gowda; and&lt;br&gt;&#13;
6) Samajwadi Janata Party (SJP).&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;Samajwadi Party leader Mulayam Singh Yadav has been authorised by the parties to oversee and plan the merger, according to &lt;a href="http://timesofindia.indiatimes.com/india/No-hiccups-in-Janata-Parivar-merger-KC-Tyagi/articleshow/46769486.cms"&gt;media reports&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;The immediate focus of the new party would be the elections to the 243-seat Bihar assembly scheduled for the end of the year.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;Here are the seat positions of the six parties in the Lok Sabha, Rajya Sabha and state assemblies.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;</value>
    </content>
    <image>&lt;img href='ModiCharismatable1.jpg' /&gt;</image>
    <width>617</width>
    <height>235</height>
    <content>
      <value>&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;The new party will have 15 members in the Lok Sabha and 30 in the Rajya Sabha.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;So, will this be a redux of the grand experiment of 1977 &amp;#8211; Janata Party.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;For next-gen readers, here is a flashback to India&amp;#8217;s political past:&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;Indian Prime Minister Mrs. Indira Gandhi imposed a state of emergency in the country after she lost a case in 1975. An Allahabad High Court verdict found her guilty of using corrupt electoral practices to win an &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Indian_general_election,_1971"&gt;election in 1971&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;Opposition leaders, including Jayaprakash Narayan, Jivatram Kripalani and Morarji Desai, led the resistance movement, which led to the formation of Janata Party to contest the general elections in 1977.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Janata_Party"&gt;The Janata party&lt;/a&gt; was officially launched on 23 January 1977 when Janata Morcha, Charan Singh&amp;#8217;s Bharatiya Lok Dal, Swatantra Party, Socialist Party of India of Raj Narain and George Fernandes and the Bharatiya Jana Sangh (BJS) joined together.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;Morarji Desai was elected the first party chairman, Ramakrishna Hegde became the party general secretary and Jana Sangh leader Lal Krishna Advani became the party spokesperson.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;Janata Party swept the polls, and Congress was ousted from power in India for the first time after 30 years of independence in 1977.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;Now here is a rewind of history:&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;While &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Janata_Party"&gt;Janata Party&lt;/a&gt; swept the elections in northern India, the Congress could still win over 150 seats, mainly due to its victories in southern India.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;And a similar&amp;nbsp;scenario unfolded in the 2014 elections.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;While Bharatiya Janata Party (BJP), a successor to Jana Sangh, won &lt;a href="http://eci.nic.in/eci_main/archiveofge2014/20%20-%20Performance%20of%20National%20Parties.pdf"&gt;282 seats&lt;/a&gt;, mainly from the North, Congress won majority of its seats from South India, as &lt;strong&gt;IndiaSpend&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="http://www.indiaspend.com/special-reports/south-india-to-congress-rescue-again-60545"&gt;reported&lt;/a&gt; earlier.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;While the two political scenarios are not comparable, can the coming together of six regional forces in north, east and south change the electoral dynamics?&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;Will the new alliance be able to swing the voters&amp;#8217; mood in Bihar? Has the Modi Magic waned?&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;While the Janata Party experiment could not last more than three years (the party was split by then and Mrs. Gandhi won the general elections in 1980 with a thumping majority), will the 6-party alliance work this time?&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;We will know by the end of this year.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;_________________________________________________&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;#8220;Liked this story? Indiaspend.org is a non-profit, and we depend on readers like you to drive our public-interest journalism efforts. &lt;a href="http://www.indiaspend.com/donate1"&gt;Donate&lt;/a&gt; Rs 500; Rs 1,000, Rs 2,000.&amp;#8221;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
</value>
    </content>
  </article>
</indiaspend>
