<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<indiaspend>
  <article>
    <title>No person As Squeezed In As The Mumbaikar</title>
    <authorname>A Staff Writer</authorname>
    <date>November 23, 2014</date>
    <category>Politics</category>
    <image>&lt;img href='mumbaikarcoverimageg.j.jpg' /&gt;</image>
    <width>600</width>
    <height>420</height>
    <content>
      <value>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;(A view of Hanging Garden in south Mumbai)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;A visit to any open area in Mumbai reveals what the locals, known as Mumbaikars, really crave &amp;#8212; open space. Every playground, every promenade and every park is packed, revealing what they lack&amp;#8212;open space.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;Every person in Mumbai has access to just 12 sq ft of open space, which includes gardens, parks, recreation grounds and playgrounds.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;It isn&amp;#8217;t much better for living space.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;A&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href="http://cdn.bmwguggenheimlab.org/Your_Place_My_Place_or_Our_Public_Space.pdf"&gt;report&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;by BMW Guggenheim Lab reveals Mumbaikars have a living area of 48 sq ft per person as compared to 111.5 sq.ft in Shanghai, 1,124 sq.ft in New York and 2,248 sq.ft in Washington D.C.&lt;/p&gt;</value>
    </content>
    <image>&lt;img href='mumbaikargraph1.jpg' /&gt;</image>
    <width>629</width>
    <height>430</height>
    <content>
      <value>&lt;p&gt;The report said: &amp;#8220;In a city where within the span of a day, a public street can transform from a crowded place of transport to a vibrant market to a gathering space for group prayer and back again to its original state, flexibility is essential for city dwellers. It seems natural that Mumbaikars&amp;#700; attitudes towards privacy and the spaces in which it is achieved would also be in a constant state of change.&amp;#8221;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;The study said that Mumbai&amp;#8217;s citizens found privacy in public places like beachfront spaces, parks, bus stops, zoning out in local trains, mosques and markets. While 54% of the 800 respondents to the study considered &amp;#8220;home&amp;#8221; to be their most private space, many participants said that they do not feel comfortable speaking about private matters at home, since it is so cramped and small.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;(Image Credit: Flickr)&amp;nbsp;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;__________________________________________________________&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;#8220;Liked this story? Indiaspend.org is a non-profit, and we depend on readers like you to drive our public-interest journalism efforts. &lt;a href="http://www.indiaspend.com/donate1"&gt;Donate &lt;/a&gt;Rs 500; Rs 1,000, Rs 2,000.&amp;#8221;&lt;/p&gt;</value>
    </content>
  </article>
</indiaspend>
