<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<indiaspend>
  <article>
    <title>Top 10 New Schemes Explained</title>
    <authorname>Abheet Singh Sethi</authorname>
    <date>February 28, 2015</date>
    <category>Politics</category>
    <image>&lt;img href='NewSchemescoverimage.jpg' /&gt;</image>
    <width>620</width>
    <height>405</height>
    <content>
      <value>&lt;p&gt;The 2015 &lt;a href="http://indiabudget.nic.in/ub2015-16/bs/bs.pdf"&gt;Union Budget&lt;/a&gt; presented by Finance Minister Arun Jaitley saw the introduction of new schemes across multiple sectors.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;The list is topped by Micro Units Development Refinance Agency (MUDRA) Bank with an initial corpus of Rs. 20,000 crore and a credit guarantee corpus of Rs 3,000 crore. MUDRA bank will act as a re-finance agency providing lending priority to SC/ST businesses through the &lt;em&gt;Pradhan Mantri Mudra Yojana&lt;/em&gt; (Prime Minister&amp;#8217;s Micro Units Development Programme).&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;National Investment and Infrastructure Fund (NIIF) will be provided Rs 20,000 crore for boosting infrastructure investments.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Pradhan Mantri Krishi Sinchai Yojana&lt;/em&gt; (Prime Minister&amp;#8217;s Irrigation Programme) has been allocated Rs. 1,800 crore. The programme will provide support to micro-irrigation and watershed development. This will also cover the &amp;#8216;per drop more crop programme&amp;#8217; under the department of agriculture and co-operation.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;Another important scheme for agriculture is the &lt;em&gt;Paramparagat Krishi Vikas Yojana&lt;/em&gt; (Traditional Farming Improvement Programme) that has been allocated Rs 300 crore.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;The newly formed Ministry for Skill development has been allocated Rs. 1,500 crore (see &lt;strong&gt;IndiaSpend&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.indiaspend.com/budget-2015-modis-moment-of-reckoning/budget-2015-skilling-rural-youth-gets-rs-1500-crore-boost-23497"&gt; article&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;Several new schemes have been launched focusing on pensions and insurance.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;</value>
    </content>
    <image>&lt;img href='NewSchemestable1.jpg' /&gt;</image>
    <width>647</width>
    <height>586</height>
    <content>
      <value>&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;#8220;Liked this story? Indiaspend.org is a non-profit, and we depend on readers like you to drive our public-interest journalism efforts. &lt;a href="http://www.indiaspend.com/donate1" target="_blank"&gt;Donate&lt;/a&gt; Rs 500; Rs 1,000, Rs 2,000.&amp;#8221;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</value>
    </content>
  </article>
</indiaspend>
