<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<indiaspend>
  <article>
    <title>Can India Afford Entitlement-Driven Welfarism: N K Singh</title>
    <authorname/>
    <date>March 25, 2014</date>
    <category>Politics</category>
    <content>
      <value>&lt;p&gt;N K Singh, Member of Rajya Sabha, in conversation with Govindraj Ethiraj, at The Growth Net.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Govind&lt;/b&gt;: The economy has seen some tough times in the last five years. &amp;nbsp;The big question is how is it going to pan out now after a new Government comes in. I&amp;#8217;m joined by NK Singh, Member of Rajya Sabha, who has joined the Bharatiya Janata Party (BJP) recently.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;So, let me ask you a straight question. We&amp;#8217;ve seen tough times, we&amp;#8217;ve seen the economic growth slowdown. The question now is really more about what has to be done immediately, and then what has to be done over a slightly longer term as the new Government comes in? What is your sense?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;NK Singh&lt;/b&gt;: I have written a longish piece recently, entitled &amp;#8220;The Lost Decade&amp;#8221; which also articulates the immediate challenges of the new Government which is how to get the growth momentum back in the economy, how to revive investor confidence, how to revive expectations, and I would say that these are overarching themes. The most important challenge is how to get macro stability, now that really is the more difficult elephant in the room, of managing the fiscal deficit in a credible way because some of the things which have been mentioned so far is really a lot of accounting engineering to suggest figures of fiscal deficit than actually is the position.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Govind&lt;/b&gt;: Can you give us an example?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;NK Singh&lt;/b&gt;: For instance, a lot of known expenditure of this year has been pushed to next year. Unpaid bills of petroleum and oil companies, in their own reckoning, are Rs 35,000 crore. If you talk to agricultural experts, the suppressed bills on the food subsidy programme could exceed Rs 50,000 crore or pushed to next year. For instance, gains on revenue taken on the basis of nominal GDP growth of 13 per cent, inflation&amp;#8217;s around six per cent or so which is expected, are you expecting a GDP growth of seven per cent? If not, then the revenue figures look misaligned.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;So, I think that in terms of the quality of fiscal consolidation, people realise that a lot needs to be done.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Govind&lt;/b&gt;: So that&amp;#8217;s one part, that you can re-juggle the books so to speak, but what are the real issues?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;NK Singh&lt;/b&gt;: Well, the real issue is how to rationalise subsidies in a more meaningful way. How to really target the beneficiaries of subsidies in a more meaningful way? Are the subsidies being properly targeted? The answer would be a resounding no. Like, for instance, you take the report of the Comptroller and Auditor General on the benefits of the employment guarantee scheme known as the MGNREGA scheme. That report brings out its dark reality that the bulk of the money, which had been utilised, had been utilised for non capital creating assets, it has gone in dole programmes, which do not serve any long-term social purpose, nor sustain employment.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Govind&lt;/b&gt;: So, there is a thematic question there, and an operational question there. Let me ask you the thematic question first. Do you think that flagship programmes have served their purpose? If so, to what extent and if not, then why?&lt;/p&gt;</value>
    </content>
  </article>
</indiaspend>
