<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<indiaspend>
  <article>
    <title>Fewer Nuclear Warheads? Why India Shouldn’t Worry</title>
    <authorname>Gaurav Jeyaraman </authorname>
    <date>April 10, 2015</date>
    <category>Politics</category>
    <image>&lt;img href='NuclearWarheadscoverimage.jpg' /&gt;</image>
    <width>620</width>
    <height>408</height>
    <content>
      <value>&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;Should India be worried that it has fewer nuclear warheads than neighbours Pakistan and China, a subject of &lt;a href="http://www.timesnow.tv/Pakistan-has-10-more-nuclear-weapons-than-India-Report/articleshow/4474109.cms"&gt;recent&lt;/a&gt; discussion?&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;div style="width:625px;margin-top:15px"&gt;&lt;div id="InRead"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Maybe not.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;India has boosted its nuclear triad&amp;#8211;nuclear-armed strike aircraft, land-based inter-continental ballistic missiles (ICBMs) and sea-based submarine-launched ballistic missiles (SLBMs)&amp;#8211;and now has a strong nuclear deterrence capability &lt;em&gt;vis-a-vis&lt;/em&gt; its nuclear-armed neighbours.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;#8220;Such [a triad] essentially increases the deterrence potential of the state&amp;#8217;s nuclear forces,&amp;#8221; &lt;a href="http://www.idsa.in/occasionalpapers/IndiasNuclearTriad.html"&gt;write&lt;/a&gt; Group Captain Ajay Lele (retd.) and Parveen Bhardwaj of the Institute of Defence Studies and Analysis (IDSA), a New Delhi think tank.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;Given that a nuclear warhead with a yield of 1 megaton can destroy almost &lt;a href="http://www.atomicarchive.com/Effects/effects1.shtml"&gt;210 sq km&lt;/a&gt;, roughly three times the &lt;a href="http://www.britannica.com/EBchecked/topic/72526/Mumbai"&gt;size&lt;/a&gt; of South Mumbai, it is largely inconsequential if Pakistan has 10 more warheads than India or China has 140 more, as &lt;a href="http://thebulletin.org/nuclear-notebook-multimedia"&gt;data&lt;/a&gt; released by the Bulletin of Atomic Scientists, a US advocacy that tracks global nuclear arsenals, reveals.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;Pakistan has also been recognised as having the world&amp;#8217;s fastest growing nuclear arsenal, which, according to &lt;a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2015/04/06/opinion/nuclear-fears-in-south-asia.html"&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; &lt;em&gt;New York Times&lt;/em&gt; editorial, is turning South Asia into a &amp;#8220;troubled region with growing nuclear risks.&amp;#8221;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
</value>
    </content>
    <image>&lt;img href='NuclearWarheadsgraph1.jpg' /&gt;</image>
    <width>520</width>
    <height>326</height>
    <content>
      <value>&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;Having more warheads than your opponent does not necessarily translate to greater security.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;This is largely because nuclear weapons are weapons of mass destruction, meant primarily to scare and deter, usually ending in a &lt;a href="http://www.atomicarchive.com/History/coldwar/page15.shtml"&gt;situation&lt;/a&gt; of strategic stalemate between countries that possess nuclear weapons.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;Nuclear weapons were used only twice in battle, 69 years ago, dropped on the Japanese cities of Hiroshima and Nagasaki, and never since.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;The possibility of &amp;#8220;mutually assured destruction&amp;#8221;, or MAD, as it is commonly known,also prevents their use in the subcontinent.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Indian nuclear triad grows stronger&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;India&amp;#8217;s nuclear-strike capability is strong because it has multiple strike aircraft, such as the nuclear-capable Anglo-French Jaguar, French Dassault Mirage 2000 and the Russian Sukhoi 30 MKI aircraft (being &lt;a href="http://www.business-standard.com/article/current-affairs/brahmos-with-sukhoi-30-fighters-to-improve-india-s-strike-options-114042201446_1.html"&gt;upgraded&lt;/a&gt; to carry the nuclear-tipped supersonic Brahmos missile).&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;Its land-based ballistic missiles include the Agni V with a range of 5,000 km, which means it can reach all of China. The Agni V can be launched from a mobile transporter or a special railway wagon, so it can be kept hidden and moved at will, according to this &lt;a href="http://www.ndtv.com/india-news/agni-5-indias-most-potent-nuclear-capable-ballistic-missile-launched-successfully-534643"&gt;report&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;The third component of the triad is under &lt;a href="http://thediplomat.com/2014/06/indias-nuclear-triad-finally-coming-of-age/"&gt;development&lt;/a&gt;, nuclear-powered Arihant class submarines that are capable of launching the 700-km range K-15 Sagarika ballistic missile and the 3,000-km range K-4 ballistic missile.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;China possesses a nuclear triad, but Pakistan, which lacks sea-launch capability, does not.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;No first use: India&amp;#8217;s Nuclear Doctrine&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;No first use. That&amp;#8217;s the declared essence of India&amp;#8217;s nuclear doctrine, &lt;a href="http://pib.nic.in/archieve/lreleng/lyr2003/rjan2003/04012003/r040120033.html"&gt;adopted&lt;/a&gt; in January 2003.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;It says India will use atomic weapons &amp;#8220;in retaliation against a nuclear attack on Indian territory or on Indian forces anywhere&amp;#8221;. The retaliation, said the report, &amp;#8220;will be massive and designed to inflict unacceptable damage&amp;#8221;.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;India also declares it will not use nuclear weapons against non-nuclear weapon states. According to the &lt;a href="http://mea.gov.in/in-focus-article.htm?18916/Draft+Report+of+National+Security+Advisory+Board+on+Indian+Nuclear+Doctrine#objectives"&gt;draft&lt;/a&gt; of the nuclear doctrine, India needs &amp;#8220;sufficient, survivable and operationally-prepared nuclear forces&amp;#8221;.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;#8220;Used in conjunction with the concepts of &amp;#8220;No First Use&amp;#8221; and &amp;#8220;Non Use&amp;#8221; against non-nuclear weapon states, it clearly indicates that India envisages its nuclear weapons as only a deterrent merely for defensive purposes and not as a means to threaten others,&amp;#8221; &lt;a href="http://www.idsa.in/issuebrief/RevisitingIndiasNuclearDoctrine_schandra_300414.html"&gt;writes&lt;/a&gt; Satish Chandra, former deputy national security advisor.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Why India built nuclear weapons&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;The world first witnessed the destructive capability of nuclear weapons in 1945, when the US bombed Hiroshima and Nagasaki, killing approximately &lt;a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/history/ww2peopleswar/timeline/factfiles/nonflash/a6652262.shtml"&gt;2,00,000&lt;/a&gt; people. The event was a reference point for debates on the political nature of nuclear weapons.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;Under Prime Minister Jawaharlal Nehru, India&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href="http://charnysh.net/Documents/charnysh_india_analysis.pdf"&gt;pursued&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;a policy of aversion toward nuclear-weapons technology. However, with the assistance of the United States and Canada, India actively pursued its nuclear-energy programme.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;The 1962 Sino-Indian war, and China&amp;#8217;s decision to conduct nuclear tests in 1964, led Prime Minister Lal Bahadur Shastri to authorise the theoretical framework for what was&amp;#8211;ironically&amp;#8211;termed a Subterranean Nuclear Explosion for Peaceful Purposes (SNEPP).&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="http://charnysh.net/Documents/charnysh_india_analysis.pdf"&gt;SNEPP&lt;/a&gt; culminated in Pokhran I, India&amp;#8217;s first &amp;#8216;peaceful&amp;#8217; nuclear explosion on May 18, 1974, when Indira Gandhi was Prime Minister.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;While the yield of the test has been the subject of debate among academicians, the test proved India&amp;#8217;s capability to weaponise nuclear technology.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;The plutonium used for the device was obtained from the Canada-India-US Research Reactor (heavy water for the reactor came from the US), according to the&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href="http://fas.org/nuke/guide/india/nuke/index.html"&gt;Federation of American Scientists&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;This led to international sanctions on India, which severely hampered India&amp;#8217;s nuclear weapons programme. More importantly, this event led to the creation of the&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href="http://www.nuclearsuppliersgroup.org/en/"&gt;Nuclear Suppliers Group&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;After a 24-year pause, India conducted five nuclear weapons tests in May 1998 when Atal Behari Vajpayee was Prime Minister. The tests were followed by a self-declared moratorium on further nuclear tests.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;Pakistan successfully conducted its first nuclear weapons tests less than three weeks later.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;(&lt;strong&gt;Jeyaraman&lt;/strong&gt; is Producer/News writer at &lt;a href="http://boomlive.in/"&gt;Boom Live&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;strong&gt;Sethi&lt;/strong&gt; is an analyst at IndiaSpend.)&lt;/em&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;br&gt;&#13;
_____________________________________________________________________&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;#8220;Liked this story? Indiaspend.org is a non-profit, and we depend on readers like you to drive our public-interest journalism efforts. &lt;a href="http://www.indiaspend.com/donate1" target="_blank"&gt;Donate&lt;/a&gt; Rs 500; Rs 1,000, Rs 2,000.&amp;#8221;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
</value>
    </content>
  </article>
</indiaspend>
