<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<indiaspend>
  <article>
    <title>In Underground Rock Caverns, Tanks, India Builds Oil Reserves</title>
    <authorname>Abheet Singh Sethi</authorname>
    <date>April 23, 2015</date>
    <category>Economy</category>
    <image>&lt;img href='OilReservesCoverImage' /&gt;</image>
    <width>620</width>
    <height>342</height>
    <content>
      <value>&lt;div style="width:625px;margin-top:15px"&gt;&lt;div id="InRead"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Two giant, rock-cut caverns will soon be pumped full of crude oil in the eastern port of Vishakhapatnam, part of a set of new underground facilities that will hold India&amp;#8217;s emergency oil reserves.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;Taking advantage of weak global crude prices, down about &lt;a href="http://www.investing.com/commodities/brent-oil-advanced-chart"&gt;42.5%&lt;/a&gt; since July 2014, the government is spending about Rs 4,948 crore ($800 million) to shore up what are called strategic oil reserves, which can be used in emergencies, if crude imports are disrupted.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;The new storage facilities, &lt;a href="http://articles.economictimes.indiatimes.com/2013-09-27/news/42463921_1_isprl-india-strategic-petroleum-visakhapatnam-facility"&gt;approved&lt;/a&gt; on January 2006, include:&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;ul&gt;&#13;
&lt;li&gt;Apart from the natural caverns, concrete tanks are being built at Vishakhapatnam port. Both underground facilities can together hold 1.33 metric tonnes (MMT) of crude&amp;#8212;the equivalent of 1,29,221 truck-tanker loads.&lt;/li&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;li&gt;Money left over after filling the Vishakhapatnam storage will be used to buy more crude to fill two more facilities at Mangalore and Padur, both in Karnataka on India&amp;#8217;s western coast.&lt;/li&gt;&#13;
&lt;/ul&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;</value>
    </content>
    <image>&lt;img href='OilReservesImage1' /&gt;</image>
    <width>500</width>
    <height>284</height>
    <content>
      <value>&lt;p style="font-size: 12px;margin-left:60px;width:500px;"&gt;&lt;em&gt; A series of pipes running from the surface (above) descend into the underground rock caverns (below). Crude oil will be pumped into the caverns through these pipes. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Image Credit:&lt;/strong&gt; Indian Strategic Petroleum Reserves Ltd  &lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;</value>
    </content>
    <image>&lt;img href='OilReservesImage2' /&gt;</image>
    <width>500</width>
    <height>318</height>
    <content>
      <value>&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;Put together, the three facilities&amp;#8212;managed by the &lt;a href="http://www.isprlindia.com/"&gt;Indian Strategic Petroleum Reserves Ltd&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#8212;can hold 5.33 MMT of crude oil, the equivalent of 5,17,857 truck-tanker loads (of &lt;a href="http://www.motorindiaonline.in/applications/tata-motors-leading-the-way-with-ready-to-use-tankers/"&gt;12&lt;/a&gt; kilolitre capacity each).&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;The strategic reserves would hold enough crude oil to power India for about 13 days, based on current net oil imports, according to data tabled in &lt;a href="164.100.47.234/question/qhindi/232/Au365.docx"&gt;Rajya Sabha&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
</value>
    </content>
    <image>&lt;img href='OilReservesTable1' /&gt;</image>
    <width>645</width>
    <height>194</height>
    <content>
      <value>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Why India needs emergency oil reserves&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;In 2014-2015, India will import 83% of its total (228.41 MMT) oil requirement, according to &lt;a href="http://planningcommission.nic.in/reports/genrep/rep_intengy.pdf"&gt;data&lt;/a&gt; released by the Ministry of Petroleum and Natural Gas.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;Over five years, India has imported more than 80% of its crude-oil requirement.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;</value>
    </content>
    <image>&lt;img href='OilReservesGraph1' /&gt;</image>
    <width>692</width>
    <height>349</height>
    <content>
      <value>&lt;p&gt;The erstwhile Planning Commission (now NITI Aayog), in its &lt;a href="http://planningcommission.nic.in/reports/genrep/rep_intengy.pdf"&gt;Integrated Energy Policy&lt;/a&gt;, 2006, announced, supply, market and technical risks as major threats to India&amp;#8217;s energy security. It recommended that India &amp;#8220;maintain a reserve equivalent to 90 days of oil imports for strategic-cum-buffer stock purposes&amp;#8221;.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;India will require additional crude-oil storage of approximately 13.32 MMT by 2019-20, according to rough estimates, based on existing storage with oil companies and the new facilities being built by ISPRL.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;Therefore, the Indian government is planning to build four more facilities for strategic crude reserves at Chandikhol (Orissa), Bikaner, Rajkot and Padur, with a combined storage capacity of 12.5 MMT of crude oil, according to ISPRL data.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;</value>
    </content>
    <image>&lt;img href='OilReservesGraph2' /&gt;</image>
    <width>670</width>
    <height>343</height>
    <content>
      <value>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;India makes a start, others ahead&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;The global standard for strategic oil reserves, as set by International Energy Association (IEA) for member-countries, is 90 days of net oil imports.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;USA holds 95 MMT of strategic reserves, the highest by any country in the world.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;Japan, which like India is dependent on imported oil, has the second highest reserves with 44 MMT  (These reserves exclude commercial storage of crude oil).&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;</value>
    </content>
    <image>&lt;img href='OilReservesGraph3' /&gt;</image>
    <width>616</width>
    <height>349</height>
    <content>
      <value>&lt;p&gt;China, like India, is in the process of shoring up its strategic oil reserves. As of November 2014, it had acquired 12.4 MMT.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;br /&gt;&#13;
__________________________________________________________________&lt;br /&gt;&#13;
&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;#8220;Liked this story? Indiaspend.com is a non-profit, and we depend on readers like you to drive our public-interest journalism efforts. &lt;a href="http://www.indiaspend.com/donate1" target="_blank"&gt;Donate&lt;/a&gt; Rs 500; Rs 1,000, Rs 2,000.&amp;#8221;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
</value>
    </content>
  </article>
</indiaspend>
