<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<indiaspend>
  <article>
    <title>Assam Beats Kerala In Primary Education Outcomes</title>
    <authorname>IS Staff</authorname>
    <date>June 20, 2014</date>
    <category>Education</category>
    <content>
      <value>&lt;p&gt;There is a great deal of focus now on education outcomes. Given this trend, the following figures might come as a surprise.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;When it comes to primary education, the north eastern state of Assam, which has an overall literacy rate of 72.19%, is ranked No 1 in outcomes at the primary school level, according to a report of the Ministry of Human Resources.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;Assam is also ahead of Kerala, which has a literacy rate of 95.72% and is ranked No 29 in outcomes. Usually, it is assumed that Kerala would lead in outcomes thanks to its overall lead in literacy levels.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;Karnataka at No 2, Chhatisgarh at No 3, Tamil Nadu at No 4 and Jharkhand at 5 are the other states which might surprise some.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-size: 13px;"&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;Outcomes have been based on various parameters including transition from primary to upper primary, gross enrolment ratio and drop-out rate.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;These figures are from the &lt;a href="http://dise.in/"&gt;Flash Statistics for 2013-14&lt;/a&gt; released under District Information System for Education (DISE). Assam and Kerala are followed by Chhattisgarh, Tamil Nadu and Jharkhand.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
</value>
    </content>
    <image>&lt;img href='PrimaryEducationtable1.jpg' /&gt;</image>
    <width>661</width>
    <height>173</height>
    <content>
      <value>&lt;p&gt;While Meghalaya is ranked No 1 in access, Karnataka has the best infrastructure and Lakshadweep tops the list for teachers.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;If we look at the composite &amp;nbsp;(primary + upper primary level) educational development index for all schools and all managements for primary and upper primary, Puducherry is ranked No 1 followed by Lakshadweep and Sikkim.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
</value>
    </content>
    <image>&lt;img href='PrimaryEducationtable2.jpg' /&gt;</image>
    <width>655</width>
    <height>192</height>
    <content>
      <value>&lt;p&gt;(Copy updated to &amp;nbsp;reflect &amp;nbsp;corrected version of the story that was first published on June 20, 2014)&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
</value>
    </content>
  </article>
</indiaspend>
