<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<indiaspend>
  <article>
    <title>Rail Budget 2014: New Ways To Pick Up The Tab</title>
    <authorname>Prachi Salve </authorname>
    <date>July 8, 2014</date>
    <category>Politics</category>
    <image>&lt;img href='railbudgetcoverimage.jpg' /&gt;</image>
    <width>1574</width>
    <height>1443</height>
    <content>
      <value>Railway Minister D V Sadananda Gowda &lt;a href="http://pib.nic.in/archieve/others/2014/jul/rbEngspeech.pdf"&gt;presented the first Budget&lt;/a&gt; of the Narendra Modi-led National Democratic Alliance (NDA) Government. Gowda has set the tone for NDA&amp;#8217;s Budget exercise with &amp;nbsp;minimal populism (translated: no fare hikes) but promises for better amenities, attempt to meet poll promises like bullet and high-speed trains and move towards alternate sources of revenue generation and funding. The last might be the most distinguishing factor of this time&amp;#8217;s Rail Budget.&lt;/p&gt;</value>
    </content>
    <image>&lt;img href='railbudgetgraph1.jpg' /&gt;</image>
    <width>626</width>
    <height>326</height>
    <content>
      <value>&lt;p&gt;The number of passengers using the railways declined by 46 million in 2013-14 and earnings declined Rs 968 crore from revised estimates.&amp;nbsp; And rail freight continued to come down as a share of total freight traffic.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;Gross traffic receipts at Rs 1,39,558 crore, though short of RE by Rs 942 crore, increased by 12.8% over the previous year. The recent fare and tariff hike (announced in June 2014) is likely to garner additional revenue of about Rs 8,000 crore.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;The Government is planning to look at resource mobilisation in the following ways:&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;* Leverage PSUs&amp;#8217; resources by bringing in their investible surplus funds in infrastructure projects of the railways.&lt;br&gt;&#13;
* Attract domestic investments and FDI in rail infrastructure.&lt;br&gt;&#13;
* Pursue Public-Private Partnership (PPP).&lt;br&gt;&#13;
* Set up private freight terminal on PPP model to develop network of freight terminals.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;The Railways Minister said the total expenditure for the current financial year would be Rs 1,64,374 crore. &amp;nbsp;Ordinary working expenses are expected to be Rs 1,12,649 crore, which would be Rs 15,078 crore higher than 2013-14. The reason for the increase has been cited as the fuel price hike and increase in staff cost.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;The table below shows the major heads of expenditure of railways, and the total expenditure for 2013-14, interim rail budget 2014 and proposed expenditures for 2014-15.&lt;/p&gt;</value>
    </content>
    <image>&lt;img href='railbudgetgraph2.jpg' /&gt;</image>
    <width>628</width>
    <height>326</height>
    <content>
      <value>&lt;p&gt;The plan outlay proposed at Rs 47,650 crore is higher by Rs 9,383 crore over 2013-14. The finance ministry has extended an additional budgetary support of Rs 1,100 crore as capital and Rs 273 crore as railway&amp;#8217;s share from diesel cess.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;Safety works take up a large share of expenses with Rs 40,000 crore allocated for passenger safety. The Government plans to do away with all unmanned rail crossings which will be substituted by Road-under-bridges and Road-over-bridges for which Rs 1,785 crore has been allocated. There is also a stress on cleanliness and improvement of service levels. In keeping with this, expenditure has been increased in the budget by 40% over the previous year.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;Regionally, there is a stress on projects in North-East with a total allocation of Rs 5,116 crore. Telangana and Andhra Pradesh have been allocated an estimated amount of Rs 20,680 crore for railway development projects.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;There is a stress on port connectivity with rail with a total expenditure outlay of Rs 4,000 crore. The minister has also proposed a diamond quadrilateral high speed rail network with an initial allocation of Rs 100 crore for a high speed link between Mumbai and Ahmedabad.&lt;/p&gt;</value>
    </content>
  </article>
</indiaspend>
