<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<indiaspend>
  <article>
    <title>Railways, Coal Transport Are Not Side Issues, They Are Core Issues: Rakesh Mohan</title>
    <authorname/>
    <date>March 26, 2014</date>
    <category>Politics</category>
    <content>
      <value>&lt;p&gt;Dr Rakesh Mohan, executive director, International Monetary Fund, in conversation with Govindraj Ethiraj at Growth Net.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Govind&lt;/b&gt;: There is political change on the Indian horizon. Does that also mean there&amp;#8217;s economic change ahead? What are the preconditions, as we sit here today, at much lower growth rates than ever before or at least in recent times? Is the stage set for a recovery or are there challenges still ahead? If I were to ask you to cast your eye on the economic landscape in India, what are the key challenges you see and what are the factors that augur well?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Rakesh Mohan&lt;/b&gt;: Let me divide my remarks into two segments: first macro-economic stabilization, and second more structural issues.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The first, what I might call standard macro-economic stabilisation, is that it is absolutely necessary to bring down inflation in the country. I think one of the facts that is not appreciated enough is that from around 1996-97 till around 2007-08, for almost ten years, we succeeded in maintaining an average inflation of around 4.5-5%. Not double digits, single digits, around 4.5-5%. When inflation is 4.5-5%, then normal interest rates could be lowered.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Govind&lt;/b&gt;: The single digit inflation was till?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Rakesh Mohan&lt;/b&gt;: From around 1996-97 till about 2007-08.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Govind&lt;/b&gt;: Okay, I meant the period after that.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Rakesh Mohan&lt;/b&gt;: I&amp;#8217;m saying that point is not realised enough. That was a major ingredient of the kind of growth we achieved during those years, particularly, of course, from 2003 to 2008. As inflation came down, inflation expectations came down, and interest rates could also come down. And, therefore, you could have reasonable nominal interest rates.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;You can&amp;#8217;t have inflation at eight, nine, ten per cent, and interest rates, as often the private sector wants, at 8-9% because then the savers get nothing. And you&amp;#8217;ve sort of seen our savings rate go down. So, let&amp;#8217;s say the first issue really is, that both from the fiscal side as well as from the monetary side, we can&amp;#8217;t think of getting the kind of growth we have achieved in the past, on a sustainable basis, unless we can get inflation down on a sustainable basis. Now I&amp;#8217;m not going to go into what you need to do for that because that&amp;#8217;s a longer discussion, but nonetheless, it does mean that you have to bring the fiscal under control. Of course, that&amp;#8217;s been in action but one of the things that are very often not talked about is that our revenue-GDP ratio, tax revenue-GDP ratio, is no higher today than it was 25 years ago.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Incomes have increased tremendously in the last 25 years. So, even if you keep most things constant, just by the fact of incomes increasing, so much more transactions, both indirect tax and direct tax ratios should go up. And they have not. In fact, today, the revenue-GDP ratio is lower than it was five years ago. So, part of the deficit reduction is not just cutting expenditure but you have to increase revenue. It&amp;#8217;s not raising tax rates, it just means greater efficiency in collection and much greater compliance. It has to be enforced. Taxes today are reasonable, they&amp;#8217;ve been stable, relatively speaking. Maximum personal tax is thirty per cent thereabouts, similarly corporate tax rate, and those are reasonable tax rates.&lt;/p&gt;</value>
    </content>
  </article>
</indiaspend>
