<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<indiaspend>
  <article>
    <title>How Production In Reliance’s KG-D6 Oil Wells Is Falling</title>
    <authorname>Amit Bhandari</authorname>
    <date>April 29, 2014</date>
    <category>Politics</category>
    <image>&lt;img href='reliancecoverimage.jpg' /&gt;</image>
    <width>736</width>
    <height>434</height>
    <content>
      <value>&lt;p&gt;Reliance Industries, India&amp;#8217;s largest private sector company, is at the center of a gas pricing storm. Meanwhile, natural gas production from the company&amp;#8217;s KG-D6 gas fields off the east coast of India continues to fall, and is a fraction of what it was three to four years ago.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;Several &amp;#8216;conspiracy theories&amp;#8217; have begun doing the rounds including one that Reliance is &amp;#8216;hoarding&amp;#8217; the natural gas and waiting for the Government to revise the price upwards. This seems unlikely though. More likely, the gas is plain running out.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;IndiaSpend tried to look at production trends, company announcements and information given out by the Government to understand the facts. Natural gas production from KG-D6 started in FY10 and saw its peak production in FY11. Ever since, natural gas and oil production has fallen every single year.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;The FY14 financial results of Reliance give details of the natural gas production from the gas fields. For the full year, the KG-D6 field produced 178 billion cubic feet (bcf) of natural gas, which is less than a quarter of the production in FY11 &amp;#8211; just after the field had become operational.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;In its press release, the company attributes this fall to &amp;#8220;the geological complexity and natural decline in the fields and higher than envisaged water ingress.&amp;#8221; This is partly borne out by data released the Petroleum ministry, which gives out oil &amp;amp; gas production statistics every month.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;For the year FY14, gas production from the private sector (offshore space) was much lower than the target. The bulk of this production is from the KG-D6 field of Reliance. In its latest statement, issued in April 2014, the ministry states: &amp;#8220;A total of 10 wells in D1, D3 and 2 wells in MA have ceased to flow due to water /sand ingress in KG-DWN-98/3 field.&amp;#8221; D1, D3 and MA are all fields in the KG-D6 block.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;Older statements of the ministry going back a couple of years also refer to well closures because of this factor &amp;#8211; the number of wells that have had to be closed has kept on increasing over the years. Water/sand can leak into oil &amp;amp; gas wells for a variety of reasons. One possible factor is that the pressure of oil/gas inside the well has fallen to a low level, and is not enough to keep these out. Low pressure can be a sign of the well running low on hydrocarbons. Water and sand ingress into a well is not something the field operator can usually control.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;The other factor of note is that the reserve estimates of the KG-D6 have also been downgraded once. In any oil &amp;amp; gas field, reserves are classified in different ways. There is the &amp;#8216;in-place&amp;#8217; reserve &amp;#8211; which is the total quantity of oil &amp;amp; gas, present underground, and then there are the &amp;#8216;recoverable reserves&amp;#8217;, which can be produced at the current level of technology and prices.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;In August 2012, the Petroleum Ministry informed the Parliament that prior to commencing the work on the KG-D6 gas fields, the operator (Reliance) had estimated the recoverable reserves as 10.3 tcf (trillion cubic feet) for D1 &amp;amp; D3 fields and 681.4 bcf for MA field.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;Subsequently, the recoverable reserves were revised to 3.1 tcf for D1 &amp;amp; D3 fields and 788 bcf for MA field. Effectively, this means that the company had originally pegged the gas reserves at 10.98 tcf &amp;#8211; and had planned accordingly. These reserves, after re-evaluation, came down to 3.98 tcf &amp;#8211; less than half of the original estimate.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;This also implies that in the past five years, nearly 60% of the recoverable gas from this field has already been produced. Meanwhile, the company made its capital investments keeping in mind the earlier estimates &amp;#8211; which turned out to be optimistic. And that is perhaps where the story ends, for now.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;We would like to add (as would anyone in such a case) that there is no way to look under thousands of feet of rock and be 100% sure of what lies underneath. Oil &amp;amp; gas companies rely on methods such as seismic surveys &amp;#8211; which involve shooting sound waves into the ground and recording their echoes &amp;#8211; to judge underground rock structures.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;Scientists try to map the underground using these echoes, and then drill test wells to check their assumptions. These methods can and do go wrong at times.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
</value>
    </content>
  </article>
</indiaspend>
