<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<indiaspend>
  <article>
    <title>Can Governments Provide Basic Infra In All Schools In 6 Months?</title>
    <authorname/>
    <date>October 9, 2012</date>
    <category>Infrastructure</category>
    <image>&lt;img href='SchoolsInfracoverimage.jpg' /&gt;</image>
    <width>397</width>
    <height>216</height>
    <content>
      <value>The Supreme Court last week directed the centre and the state governments to provide basic infrastructure in all schools, including drinking water facilities and toilets, within the next six months.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;So, can this be done? In our continuing series Fact Check, &lt;strong&gt;IndiaSpend&amp;#8217;s &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;a href="mailto:danielle@indiaspend.org"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Danielle Collaco&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; takes a look at the District Information System for Education (DISE) &lt;a href="http://www.dise.in/Downloads/Publications/Publications%202010-11/Flash%20Statistics-2010-11.pdf"&gt;2010-11 Flash Statistics&lt;/a&gt; and tries to check whether this can be achieved in six months.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;First, let&amp;#8217;s take a look at the drinking water scenario. The availability of drinking water in schools seems to be almost on track. In 2010-11, about 92.7% of schools had some sort of drinking water facility. This is an increase from 92.6% in the previous year and 87.7% during 2008-09.&lt;/p&gt;</value>
    </content>
    <image>&lt;img href='SchoolsInfragraph1.jpg' /&gt;</image>
    <width>524</width>
    <height>388</height>
    <content>
      <value>&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;As you can see from the graph, the figures have been increasing over the past few years, which mean the governments may be able to meet the six-month deadline.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;#8217;s now look at the data on toilets in schools. According to the DISE report, in 2010-11, about 82.9% of all schools in India had toilets, an increase from 81.6% in 2009-10. So, the increase was barely a per cent in one year, which makes it look difficult for the governments to achieve the target of 13% increase in six months.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
</value>
    </content>
    <image>&lt;img href='SchoolsInfragraph2.jpg' /&gt;</image>
    <width>516</width>
    <height>403</height>
    <content>
      <value>&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;So, it is quite possible that the 100% target might be reached for drinking water access in all schools across the country. However, there is a chance that the governments may not be able to provide toilets in all schools within six months.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
</value>
    </content>
  </article>
</indiaspend>
