<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<indiaspend>
  <article>
    <title>Make Rs 3.78 Lakh Income Totally Tax-Free: Survey</title>
    <authorname/>
    <date>July 9, 2014</date>
    <category>Politics</category>
    <image>&lt;img href='surveycoverimage.jpg' /&gt;</image>
    <width>170</width>
    <height>160</height>
    <content>
      <value>The &amp;#8220;middle class&amp;#8221; feels that the Government must make annual income of Rs 3.78 lakh totally tax-free since Rs 31,500 is needed for an average quality of life for a family of four people.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;This was one of the key findings of a nationwide, pre-budget survey done by C-Voter. Finance Minister Arun Jaitley will present the first union budget of the Bharatiya Janata Party-led National Democratic Alliance (NDA) Government on July 10.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;Nearly 61% of those surveyed still believed that &amp;#8220;Acche Din Aane Wale Hain&amp;#8221; while 69% felt that price rise had an adverse impact on the quality of life in the last one year and 56% felt that the overall quality of life had deteriorated over the last one year.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;Now, here is something to cheer about for the Government. While only 11% of those surveyed in 2013 had said the tax money was being properly utilised, the number has doubled to 22% in 2014 &amp;#8211; a 100% increase! And 57% of those surveyed last year felt that the tax money was not being properly utilised, and the ratio declined to 44% this year &amp;#8211; a sharp drop of 13%. So, people are now feeling that the taxpayers&amp;#8217; money is being used wisely by the Government.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;Savings continue to be a worry for people: nearly 80% of those surveyed said they were not saving enough for a secure future, down from 84% in 2013.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;And here is something to ponder over for the Modi Government: 47% of those surveyed felt inflation will not come down after the budget but this is a huge drop from 83% last year.&lt;/p&gt;</value>
    </content>
  </article>
</indiaspend>
