<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<indiaspend>
  <article>
    <title>$95-Billion Tax Benefits for Companies, Individuals, Up 7%</title>
    <authorname>IndiaSpend Team</authorname>
    <date>March 3, 2015</date>
    <category>Politics</category>
    <image>&lt;img href='TaxBenefitscoverimage.jpg' /&gt;</image>
    <width>620</width>
    <height>477</height>
    <content>
      <value>&lt;p&gt;While the central government is &lt;a href="http://indiabudget.nic.in/ub2015-16/bag/bag11.pdf"&gt;expected&lt;/a&gt; to earn a tax revenue of Rs 919,842 crore ($148 billion) for the financial year 2015-16, it is expected to &lt;a href="http://indiabudget.nic.in/ub2015-16/statrevfor/annex12.pdf"&gt;forego revenue&lt;/a&gt; of Rs 589,285.2 crore ($95 billion) in 2014-15 due to exemptions granted to companies and individual taxpayers.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;This forgone revenue, or &amp;nbsp;tax benefits, is&amp;nbsp; twice the defence budget allocation of Rs 247,000 crore in 2014-15.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;Tax-revenue&amp;nbsp; forgone is a contentious issue&amp;#8211;an &amp;#8220;incentive&amp;#8221; or a &amp;#8220;sop&amp;#8221;, depending on ideological position&amp;#8211;and becoming more so at a time when the National Democratic Alliance government plans cutbacks to &lt;a href="http://indiabudget.nic.in/ub2015-16/eb/npe.pdf"&gt;India&amp;#8217;s subsidy bill&lt;/a&gt; of Rs 2,27,287 crore ($36 billion).&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;While India&amp;#8217;s subsidy bill is likely to fall almost 10%, the tax-revenue forgone is expected to increase by 7% from 2013-14.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;Those on the left hold &amp;#8220;sops&amp;#8221;&amp;#8211;such as accelerated depreciation, deduction of export profits of units located in special economic zones (SEZs), area-based exemptions and waivers on import duties&amp;#8211;as evidence of government largesse to business at the expense of the poorest. Those on the right argue that tax-revenue forgone is an important business &amp;#8220;incentive&amp;#8221; to help the economy grow, without which the needs of the poor cannot be addressed.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;Two days after &lt;a href="http://indiabudget.nic.in"&gt;Budget 2015&lt;/a&gt;, Professor Ashutosh Varshney, SoI Goldman Professor of International Studies and Social Sciences at Brown University had this twitter exchange with economist and former chief economic advisor Arvind Virmani:&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;</value>
    </content>
    <image>&lt;img href='TaxBenefitstwitter1.jpg' /&gt;</image>
    <width>526</width>
    <height>535</height>
    <content>
      <value>&lt;p&gt;Revenue forgone includes exemptions granted to companies and individual taxpayers.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;For instance, customs-duty exemptions &amp;nbsp;on precious stones and jewellery&amp;nbsp; &amp;#8211; &amp;nbsp;an effort to boost the labour-intensive industry of polished gems and jewellery , India&amp;#8217;s &lt;a href="http://rbi.org.in/Scripts/PublicationsView.aspx?Id=15919"&gt;second highest export earner&lt;/a&gt; of principal commodities, are expected to reduce government revenue by Rs 75,592 crore in 2014-15.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;Exemptions on import duties of mineral fuels and mineral oils &amp;#8212; designed to keep cost of imports low since India is totally dependent on oil imports while petro products also play a big role in exports &amp;#8211; are likely to reduce government revenue by Rs 72,180 crore.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;Individual tax payers get various deductions, such as rebates for repayment of housing loans and investments in pension funds and medical insurance.&amp;nbsp; So, for example, rebates on repayment of housing loans, investment in life insurance policies etc (categories that fall under Section 80C) will reduce revenue by Rs 29,237 crore in 2014-15.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;Given the polarised nature of the debate, some argue that many tax exemptions are wrongly listed.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;#8220;Most concessions included in revenue foregone undoubtedly contribute to enhancing public welfare or promoting exports. These should not be included in estimates of revenue forgone,&amp;#8221; &lt;a href="http://www.livemint.com/Opinion/TuZlmAlMebQ9s0GQRWvxHN/The-myth-of-foregone-revenue.html"&gt;wrote&lt;/a&gt; Rajiv Kumar and Geetima Das Krishna, senior fellow and senior researcher at the Centre for Policy Research, New Delhi, in &lt;em&gt;Mint&lt;/em&gt;. &amp;#8220;Therefore, the finance ministry would do well to come up with a new methodology for calculating the actual revenue foregone and a new nomenclature for genuinely effective tax incentives. It is important to deny the ideologues this annual &lt;em&gt;tamaasha&lt;/em&gt; (drama) of private-sector bashing.&amp;#8221;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;There&amp;#8217;s a related issue: companies are also given tax incentives, and they pay lower taxes than individuals. The larger the company, it appears, lower the tax rate.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Why do companies pay lower tax than individuals?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;Revenue forgone includes income-tax exemptions as well, almost 95% given to companies, the rest to individuals.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;The effective tax rate for 564,787 companies that filed electronic returns for the financial year 2013-14 was only 23.22% while the standard rate varies between 33.21% and 33.99%.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
</value>
    </content>
    <image>&lt;img href='TaxBenefitstable1.jpg' /&gt;</image>
    <width>647</width>
    <height>335</height>
    <content>
      <value>&lt;p&gt;The statement on revenue forgone, issued with Budget 2015, &lt;a href="http://indiabudget.nic.in/ub2015-16/statrevfor/annex12.pdf"&gt;had this to say&lt;/a&gt;: &amp;#8220;Companies with profits before taxes (PBT) of Rs 500 crore and above accounted for a total of 60.29% of the total PBT and a total of 53.71% of the total corporate income tax payable. However, their effective tax rate was 20.68% while the effective tax rate was 26.89% for companies with PBT up to Rs 1 crore.&amp;#8221;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;Clearly, bigger companies are paying lower taxes.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;Services, a growing sector of the economy, were clearly pulling their weight. Their effective tax rate was 24.37%, for instance, compared to manufacturing&amp;#8217;s tax of 21.96%.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;The revenue impact due to the major incentives offered to corporate tax payers is expected to be Rs 62,398.60 crore in 2014-15, against Rs 57,793 the previous year, an increase of 8%.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;The revenue impact of incentives given to individual tax payers, such as investments in insurance premiums, health insurance and donations, is likely to increase 15%, from Rs 30,771.8 crore in 2013-14 to Rs 35,293.6 crore in 2014-15.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;The aggregate revenue impact due to incentives for indirect taxes is expected to be Rs 486,452 crore.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;br&gt;&#13;
</value>
    </content>
    <image>&lt;img href='TaxBenefitsgraph1.jpg' /&gt;</image>
    <width>616</width>
    <height>312</height>
    <content>
      <value>&lt;p&gt;While individual tax payers account for only 6% of tax benefits, corporates, importers and exporters get 94% of such benefits.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;The 14&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt; Finance Commission, which submitted its &lt;a href="http://finmin.nic.in/14fincomm/14fcreng.pdf"&gt;report&lt;/a&gt; to the Finance Minister recently, also spoke about revenue forgone.&amp;nbsp; &amp;#8220;Revenue forgone as estimated by the Union Government reached a peak of 8.1% of GDP in 2008-09 and as a percentage of gross tax revenue, it was the highest (77.3%) in 2009-10. Since 2004-05, revenue foregone has always been in excess of 5% of GDP.&amp;#8221;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;______________________________________________________________________________&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;#8220;Liked this story? Indiaspend.org is a non-profit, and we depend on readers like you to drive our public-interest journalism efforts. &lt;a href="http://www.indiaspend.com/donate1" target="_blank"&gt;Donate&lt;/a&gt; Rs 500; Rs 1,000, Rs 2,000.&amp;#8221;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
</value>
    </content>
  </article>
</indiaspend>
