<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<indiaspend>
  <article>
    <title>Deaths Decline But Injuries Increase Due to Rail Accidents</title>
    <authorname/>
    <date>09-01-2014</date>
    <category>Select a Category</category>
    <content>
      <value>&lt;p&gt;Three coaches of the Mumbai-Dehradun Express caught fire in the wee hours on January 8, claiming the lives of 9 passengers. Railway Minister Mallikarjun Kharge announced a compensation of Rs 5 lakh to the kin of those killed in the fire, as reported in &lt;a href=\"http://economictimes.indiatimes.com/news/politics-and-nation/nine-burnt-alive-as-fire-breaks-out-in-bandra-dehradun-train/articleshow/28539441.cms\"&gt;Economic Times&lt;/a&gt;. Arunendra Kumar, Chairman of the Railway Board, has said that a compensation of Rs 1 lakh will be given to those seriously injured and Rs 50,000 will be given to passengers who suffered minor injuries.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;Wednesday&amp;#8217;s train accident is the latest in a series of accidents that have occurred in the country over the last year. A report in online portal &lt;a href=\"http://news.oneindia.in/india/death-tracks-india-saw-around-7-major-train-accidents-2013-1372535.html\"&gt;OneIndia&lt;/a&gt; highlighted 7 serious accidents have happened in 2013, the worst being the major fire on the Nanded-Bangalore Express on December 28, which claimed the lives of more than 24 passengers.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;IndiaSpend&amp;#8217;s&lt;/b&gt; analysis, however, shows that there has been a 26% &lt;a href=\"http://164.100.47.132/Annexture/lsq15/13/au5895.htm\"&gt;decline&lt;/a&gt; in the number of train accidents from 2010-11 to 2012-13. &amp;nbsp;Data from the Lok Sabha questions (which doesn&amp;#8217;t include information on Konkan Railways) shows that there were a total of 93 train accidents during 2010-11. This figure declined to 77 in 2011-12 and 68 in 2012-13. The accidents include collisions, derailments, manned level crossing accidents, incidents of fire and miscellaneous accidents.&lt;/p&gt;</value>
    </content>
    <image>&lt;img href='pic 1' /&gt;</image>
    <content>
      <value>&lt;p&gt;Northern Railways reported 16 accidents in 2010-11, which was the highest in that year. The accidents dropped to 7 in 2012-13.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;Data from the Ministry of Statistics (&lt;a href=\"http://mospi.nic.in/Mospi_New/upload/SYB2014/ch19.html\"&gt;MOSPI&lt;/a&gt;) shows that the number of passenger deaths due to train accidents has shown an uneven trend from 2007-08 to 2011-12. The number of passengers injured, however, has shot up.&lt;/p&gt;</value>
    </content>
    <image>&lt;img href='pic 2' /&gt;</image>
    <content>
      <value>&lt;p&gt;Compensation to victims of train accidents is paid only after a claim is filed with the Railway Claims Tribunal and a decree is awarded by the Tribunal. The number of cases settled has gone up by about 13% from 187 in 2010-11 to 212 in 2012-13.&lt;/p&gt;</value>
    </content>
    <image>&lt;img href='pic 3' /&gt;</image>
    <content>
      <value>&lt;p&gt;The amount of compensation has gone down by about 44% from about Rs 5.7 crore in 2010-11 to Rs 3.2 crore in 2012-13.&lt;/p&gt;</value>
    </content>
    <image>&lt;img href='pic 4' /&gt;</image>
    <content>
      <value>&lt;p&gt;As on March 2013, a total of 489 claim cases are pending with different benches of the Railway Claims Tribunal.&lt;/p&gt;</value>
    </content>
  </article>
</indiaspend>
