<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<indiaspend>
  <article>
    <title>Which Country Is The World’s Happiest? No, It’s Not India</title>
    <authorname>Sanjit Oberai</authorname>
    <date>March 25, 2014</date>
    <category>Politics</category>
    <content>
      <value>&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe src="http://www.openheatmap.com/embed.html?map=SecotiaceaeCurrenciesSpredde" height="450" width="600"&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.jetpac.com/blog/post/80147853816/the-international-day-of-happiness#.UzFvjPn1w7M" target="_blank"&gt;Jetpac&lt;/a&gt;, a social travel guide app, has come up with a ranking which tells you which is the the happiest country in the world. It analyzed more than 150 million Instagram posts across 6,000 cities worldwide to come up with a ranking of the happiest countries on the globe. The rankings were compiled by coming up with what is called a &amp;#8220;smile score&amp;#8221; for each country. This was calculated by measuring how often residents were smiling in Instagram photos. So the bigger the smile, the higher the smile score.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;div style="width:625px;margin-top:15px"&gt;&lt;div id="InRead"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&amp;#8220;Smiles on the faces of millions of people in millions of photos are the most direct measure we have of happiness. Previous attempts to measure happiness have relied on survey questions or indirect measures. Jetpac is identifying smiles on faces and then measuring the shape and size of the smile &amp;#8211; a small grin doesn&amp;#8217;t score as highly as a broad smile. Smiling for the camera seems to be a cultural norm for a country&amp;#8221;, it &lt;a href="https://www.jetpac.com/blog/post/80147853816/the-international-day-of-happiness#.UzF1vPn1w7M" target="_blank"&gt;said &lt;/a&gt;in its blog post.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;According to the results, Brazil is the most happiest place on earth with a &amp;#8216;smile score&amp;#8217; of 60.5 out of 100 in the happiness ranking while Nicaragua came a close second with 59.4 and Honduras, Colombia, Bolivia &amp;amp; Costa Rica took third, fourth and fifth and sixth place respectively.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;India was ranked 71st on the list with a smile score of 21.7 &amp;nbsp;but was ahead of Sri Lanka, China and Pakistan.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;Click on the map to know the rankings of the countries analysed.&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;(Data in map is as per rank of each country for eg. India ranks 71st out of 122 countries analysed)&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;(Note: the data above has been updated to reflect accurate data from Jetpac as many sites carried incorrect data)&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;&#13;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.jetpac.com/blog/post/80147853816/the-international-day-of-happiness#.UzJ97fn1w7M" target="_blank"&gt;Read more here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</value>
    </content>
  </article>
</indiaspend>
